<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Separation yet no schisme, or, Non-conformists no schismaticks being a full and sober vindication of the non-conformists from the charge and imputation of schisme, in answer to a sermon lately preached before the Lord Mayor by J.S.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62340</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S86</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24503</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08215541</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08215541</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41103</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62340)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41103)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1239:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Separation yet no schisme, or, Non-conformists no schismaticks being a full and sober vindication of the non-conformists from the charge and imputation of schisme, in answer to a sermon lately preached before the Lord Mayor by J.S.</title>
                  <author>J. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 71 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Erroneously attributed by Wing to J.S.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41103:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SEPARATION YET NO Schiſme: OR NON-CONFORMISTS NO SCHISMATICKS: BEING A full and Sober VINDICATION of the NON-CONFORMISTS, from the Charge and Imputation of SCHISME. IN Anſwer to a Sermon lately Preached before the Lord Mayor By <hi>J. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah. 66.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Hear the Word of the Lord, ye that tremble at his Word; your Brethren that hated you, that caſt you out for my Names ſake, ſaid, Let the Lord be glorified, but he ſhall appear to your joy, and they ſhall be aſhamed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the year, 1675.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:41103:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41103:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF thou wouldſt have a reaſon of publiſhing theſe ſheets, the Author will tell thee, That it is now about four years ſince the People he pleads for (among whom he believes there are thouſands in the Land, that are Worſhippers of God in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Truth, according to the Goſpel) have through the good Providence of their great Shepherd the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and through the granted licenſe of an indulgent Prince, enjoyed a ſweet and bleſſed Calm. But obſerving lately the Clouds a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to gather, and to have begun to diſcharge themſelves upon many of this People about <hi>England;</hi> and withal lately meeting with a Sermon, wherein this People are not ſparingly charged with Schiſm, and the penalties where with the laws threaten them, are pleaded for as very innocent harmleſs things, that Sober men (as he ſays) may be aſhamed to call perſecutions; I could not but thence conclude, that the Authors drift was to ſtir up and encourage the chief Magiſtrates of the City (for to them the Sermon was preached) to a rigorous Execution of thoſe gentle puniſhments, which are but ſuch little things as baniſhing, or impriſoning, or ſpoyling them of their Goods, and ſo undoing them and their Families, which are very trifles in his account. Now what can probably be the conſequents hereof (except the Magiſtrates as <hi>David</hi> prove wiſer than their Teachers) but that this people muſt needs be ſmitten, impoveriſhed, ſcattered, and as to their outward concernments ruined. But if this ſhall come to paſſe (and who knows what their God may permit for a time for their tryal?) what will they have left to ſupport and comfort them under ſuch preſſures, except the innocency of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and the Righteouſneſs of the cauſe for which they ſuffer. And this I ſay, whether their cauſe be good or bad, doth not as to the determination, depend upon the meer dictates of any
<pb facs="tcp:41103:3"/>Mortals; and I am very verily perſwaded, it is not prſedtſdih be bad by all this Author hath ſaid, although he ha oved to cour and reaſoned againſt it, as if (in his conceit) he had ſpoke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but demonſtrations, which I ſhould now have immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begun to reply to, but that I thought it moſt expedient, firſt to give the Reader a view of the caſe and cauſe of the Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, for which they are charged of Schiſm, and are thought to have deſerved all thoſe ſeverities which the law threatens.</p>
            <p>The Non-Conformiſts caſe is this,</p>
            <p>There are ſome hundreds of true Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, commiſſioned by him to Preach the Goſpel, and to adminiſter the Sacraments, (for ſo all true Miniſters are) thoſe according to their commiſſion do Preach, and there are many thouſands like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of viſible profeſſors of Chriſtianity, do willingly hear and joyn with theſe Miniſters in the Worſhip of God, and in a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of Sacraments as the Goſpel requires.</p>
            <p>Theſe meet in dictinct Congregations, ſeparate from the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally eſtabliſhed Congregations in the Land, with whom they Will not, becauſe they Cannot hold Communion.</p>
            <p>Becauſe they thus ſeparate and refuſe Communion they are charged with Schiſme.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why they thus ſeparate and refuſe Communion, is, becauſe they cannot have it with them; I ſay, they Cannot have it, becauſe they cannot or ought not to ſin; or to ſpeak mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly, becauſe they cannot do ſuch things which they extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuſpect to be ſinful, and if they do but ſtrongly ſuſpect them it is enough, for no man can be bound to act againſt a doubting Conſcience, and herein I have the ſuffrage of the Apoſtle, which every good Chriſtian ought much to preferre before any other who may preſume to Philoſophize to the contrary, who ſays, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. he that doubteth is damned if he eat, becauſe he eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not of Faith, for whatſoeover is not of Faith is ſin.</p>
            <p>If it be demanded, what thoſe things are which this people ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect as ſinful. It may be anſwered, they are too well known, as that any among us ſhould ſtand in need of an information: but briefly, thoſe that are Miniſters, either they ſuſpect the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of admitting a re-ordination, or of abjuring, or of aſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and conſenting to the uſe of all and every part of the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,
<pb facs="tcp:41103:3"/>and therein of every Ceremony. Now this I ſay, though the Friends of theſe impoſitions ſhall, with the higheſt confidence, affirm the lawfulneſs of them all, yea and endeavour with a thouſand arguments to prove them ſuch; yet if thoſe Miniſters herein concerned, upon a ſerious weighing of theſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments find them too light, and after much prayer to God for a reſolution, yet find themſelves to doubt, in this caſe they ought not, upon the Apoſtles rule now named, to yeild to any ſuch impoſitions againſt their doubting Conſciences.</p>
            <p>If it be here replyed, why do they not then degrade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or quietly ſuffer themſelves to be degraded of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and in the condition of private Chriſtians Communicate with this Church, for ſo they may do and free themſelves from theſe impoſitions?</p>
            <p>It will be anſwered, that this is an impoſition they ſuſpect as ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as the reſt, for ſo long as they are perſwaded that their miſſion is originally from Chriſt, they cannot believe that it is either in their own Power, or in the Power of any other Inferiour to Chriſt, to give them a diſcharge from executing this their Office, except it be for Hereſie or obſtinate ſcandal againſt ſome known laws of Chriſt, and then indeed Chriſt hath left an order, not only for excluding them from their Office, but alſo from the Church, but neither of theſe latter are in the leaſt pretended, and therefore it is they cannot without ſuſpicion of ſin, either degrad themſelves, or quietly ſuffer themſelves to be degraded. And ſtill I adde, if any reaſons be urged for the lawfulneſs of this degradati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but ſuch that are ſhort of their conviction, ſo that ſtill they doubt, it will continue yet their duty to ſerve the Church as Miniſters, and not to liſt themſelves among private Chriſtians; as is adviſed.</p>
            <p>If it be asked, but may not ſupream Magiſtrates (if they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diveſt Miniſters of their Office) may not they within their Dominion ſuſpend ſome of them from the exerciſe thereof, when they conceive it is for the Peace of the reſt?</p>
            <p>It will be anſwered, that that Lord of Lords who giveth the Office and the Commiſſion, and hath by divers Providences de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned the men thereto, hath certainly with the Office deſigned them to the exerciſe thereof, (for elſe verily the Office is in vain)
<pb facs="tcp:41103:4"/>and hath therein placed, not only the Office, but the exerciſe thereof above the reſtraint of any Powers whatever, that hold of and under him on Earth, ſo long as the exerciſe thereof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to be regulated by the laws of Chriſt. But if any men on Earth ſhall appoint new Laws, different from thoſe of Chriſts, and impoſe them on Miniſters as conditions to be obeyed, without which they will reſtrain them the exerciſe of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, as being diſturbers of the Peace; in ſuch a caſe it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that ſuch Miniſters may continue to Preach according to the Laws of Chriſt, but are reſtrained only by the Laws of men; whil'ſt then their Conſciences lye under a ſuperior obligation to Preach, than that by which they are reſtrained from Preaching, it is caſie to conceive what they will or ought to do, <hi>i. e.</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will or ought to Obey God or man.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, ſuch Miniſters are miſtaken about the nature of ſuch impoſed Laws, as if they were different from, or contrary to the Laws of Chriſt, when they are no other but what Chriſt hath intruſted them with a Power of appointing, for the Peace of his Church.</p>
            <p>It will be ſtill anſwered, that this People are perſwaded of the contrary; and that Chriſt hath not intruſted any men with ſuch a Power, but do believe that they are things rather deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive of the true Peace of the Church. And this I ſay, whil'ſt they are ſo perſwaded (though they ſhould be miſtaken) they ought not to go againſt their Conſciences; for as the Apoſtle ſaith, he that doubteth and eateth is damned. So that from the whole it is evident, the reaſon why theſe Miniſters cannot conform and why they yet continue to Preach, is, becauſe they cannot do the one, nor forbear the other without ſin; which is a juſt ground of their ſeparation, and of perſevering in the exerciſe of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and therefore ſeparation in this caſe (as to them) is no Schiſm. Some will be ready to ſay, but what is all this to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People? they are Schiſmaticks without doubt; for they have no ſuch impoſitions upon them.</p>
            <p>It may be anſwered, that if the Miniſters now named are yet true miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, and that the exerciſe of their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry hath not been according to any Law of Chriſt reſtrained, it will follow, it can be no ſin in the Diſciples of Chriſt to own them whom their Lord owneth; or to hear them whom their
<pb facs="tcp:41103:4"/>Lord hath commiſſioned to that end, and by no Law of his are reſtrained from acting according to that Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>Again, in as much as Chriſt is ſuppoſed to continue his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to theſe miniſters to Preach, it neceſſarily follows, that Chriſt hath a People to whom he ſends them: for it's abſurd to conceive, that Chriſt ſhould ſend his miniſters to preach to no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; if then they may preach, it cannot be unlawful for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to hear them, no nor to partake of any ordinance from them, which as miniſters they may adminiſter.</p>
            <p>Yet again, multitudes of the people did own them as Chriſts miniſters, and did joyn with them in all Ordinances, as ſuch, and this for ſeveral years together, and certainly during thoſe times they could not be eſteemed Schiſmaticks, for ſo doing, ſince there were no other miniſters ordinarily to be found. If then they were no Schiſmaticks, how come they to be ſo ſince? if it be ſaid the Law of the Land makes them ſuch: it may be anſwered, that ſince Schiſme (of which we ſpeak) is a ſin peculiar and proper to a Church, it is a wonder how a Law of a Land, that is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly extraneous to a Church, can make that at one time a Schiſme, which at another time cannot be ſaid to be ſuch. Nor do I think, that thoſe that now think themſelves the Church, and that all that ſeparate from them are Schiſmaticks, in caſe they had a Law of the Land to eſtabliſh Presbytery, or Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, or Anabaptiſtry, would conceive of themſelves as Schiſmaticks if they continued in that way they are in, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to hold Communion with that the Law eſtabliſhed: and in Truth I cannot poſſibly conceive how that may be ſaid juſtly to day, that it is no Schiſme, and yet to morrow it may be juſtly called ſo, meerly becauſe of an intervening humane Law.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, as for the people, it may be further anſwered, that though they be not under the ſame impoſitions as their miniſters are, yet they are not altogether free from impoſitions which they extreamly ſuſpect as ſinful: as that they cannot enjoy Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm for their Children without the Croſſe; nor receive the Lords Supper without kneeling; to name no more. If you ſay theſe are not ſinful; it is anſwered, ſuppoſe they be not, yet in caſe they ſuſpect them vehemently as ſuch, and all your argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments cannot reſolve their doubts, it is evident they would go againſt, and wound their Conſciences, in caſe they ſhould ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the one, or the other.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41103:5"/>
            <p>If therefore theſe people ſhall, for theſe reaſons, joyn with thoſe miniſters in all Ordinances, I ſee no ground to charge this people with Schiſme, no more than their miniſters.</p>
            <p>Thus having, with as much brevity as I could, ſtated the caſe and cauſe of this people, we ſhall now come to take an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Mr. <hi>J. S.</hi> his Sermon before the Mayor, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains an impeachment of Schiſm, and a pretended proof thereof againſt this people. They are now upon their tryal, and ſay, not guilty, and offer themſelvs to be tryed by the Laws of Jeſus Chriſt, which are the only Laws of his Church.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41103:5"/>
            <head>The Sermon of Mr. <hi>J. S.</hi> Examined.</head>
            <p>THE deſign of that Sermon, one would be apt to think, was to promote Peace among the Proteſtant profeſſors in <hi>England;</hi> whoſe differences are Univerſally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, to be about matters of no fundamental concernment, as to the Doctrine of Chriſtianity. His text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.19. was well ſuited to that purpoſe, <hi>Let us follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the things which make for Peace.</hi> And doubtleſſe if he had proſecuted this his deſign, by the ſame means and methods as the Apoſtle there doth, <hi>viz.</hi> not ſo much by ſetting himſelf to reſolve their controverſies, or to determine which ſide held the trueſt opinion; as to ſilence their diſputes, and to allay their bitterneſſes to each other, by ſhewing that they had nothing to do to judge or cenſure their brethren, becauſe they were Gods Servants, and to him only they ſtood or fell: and rather for Peace ſake, to forbear doing that which they might lawfully do, than by any undue uſe of their liberty to caſt a ſtumbling block before the weak uninſtructed diſſenters: This he confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>pag.</hi> 1.2. was the way the Apoſtle took, and certainly if he had followed ſo great an example, he had (like a man of Wiſdom as well as of Peace) proſecuted an excellent end by moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent means: but inſtead thereof he takes a quite contrary method, for inſtead of perſwading Chriſtians to lay aſide their Controverſies, he himſelf raiſeth them; inſtead of diſſwading them from cenſuring their brethren, as being to ſtand or fall to a higher Maſter, he cenſureth them as guilty of Schiſm; obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maintained <hi>pag.</hi> 7. And inſtead of perſwading them to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear doing thoſe things (which ſome think) they may lawfully do, (as the making uſe of preſcribed Prayers and Ceremonies) leaſt a ſtumbling block ſhould be caſt before their weak brethren, he falls pag. 5. into Encomiums of the excellency of the preſent Church Government, the eaſineſs of the Terms of Communion, the Lawfulneſs of the uſe of the publick Service, and Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41103:6"/>of the Ceremonies, and then doth conclude that Sober men ſhould be aſhamed to call the penalties which the Laws inflict on thoſe that ſeparate from the Church in theſe things, Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> of all this is, that the great Apoſtle and this Perſon are of two minds concerning theſe things which make for Peace, the Apoſtle is for not judging the Lords Servants, and he is for judging them: The Apoſtle is ſtill for holding Communion, notwithſtanding thoſe differences remain, but he is for forcing them to ſay and do as the Church doth, or elſe for pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing them with fines, impriſonments as the Laws require. But certainly, as he herein leaves the Apoſtle, ſo the Apoſtle leaves him, and in this deſerted Condition as we find him I hope it will be no preſumption to call his reaſonings about this matter to an account.</p>
            <p>The ſtrength of what he hath ſaid to juſtifie his charge of Schiſme againſt this people he hath compriſed in five Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which we ſhall examine in order.</p>
            <p>His firſt Propoſition begins pag, 10. which is this.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>That every Chriſtian upon the very account of being ſo, is a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church of Chriſt, and is bound to joyn in external Communion with it where it can be had.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>I anſwer, this Propoſition is very obſcurely laid down, nor is it releived by any light afforded in the after explication: and certainly if it be to be underſtood according to the proper mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the words and phraſes therein contained, (as it ought to be;) I ſhall not ſcruple to call the Truth thereof into Queſtion, For.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If we conſider <hi>a Chriſtian upon the very account of his being ſo,</hi> which is the Subject of the Propoſition; who can think but thereby as you phraſe it, you intend to affirm nothing of him as ſuch, but what doth neceſſarily and eſſentially belong to him, without which he could be no Chriſtian, and conſequently if he be a Chriſtian he muſt neceſſarily be a Member of Chriſts Church, in the ſence of [Church] in the Propoſition which is ſuch as therewith an external Communion may be held.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41103:6"/>
            <p>If this be your meaning, as I ſuppoſe it is, becauſe in your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of this Propoſition you ſeem to hold, that Chriſt <hi>died primarily for his Church, and but in a ſecondary ſence for individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Believers,</hi> ſo that it ſeems to follow, that none can be true Chriſtians or in a ſalvable ſtate, but as they are conſidered incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated into, and ſo made one of this Church, ſo that Church-Member-ſhip is eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ential to them. If this I ſay be your mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then give me leave to take the boldneſs to deny the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, for I cannot underſtand that a Chriſtian as ſuch, includes any eſſential relation to a Church in your ſence.</p>
            <p>That I may clear up this matter a little, give me leave to tell you that this term Chriſtian may fall under divers conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as firſt, by a Chriſtian we may underſtand a man whoſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is changed by the Preaching of the Goſpel, ſo as thereby he is of an ignorant Infidel and wicked man, made an intelligent Believer, and a good man; certainly in this ſence it is eaſie to underſtand a Chriſtian without any ſuch correlate as a Church, ſo that in this ſence a Chriſtian as ſuch, is no more related to a Church, than a man conſidered as a man, ſpeaks any Relation to a Kingdom or Common-wealth: and therefore your Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in this ſcence cannot be true.</p>
            <p>But becauſe this change of Nature, can't be wrought in any man but by the Power of God co-working with the Goſpel: and ſince this exertion of Power is called Regeneration, upon this account a Chriſtian is to be conſidered as a relative <hi>viz.</hi> as a Son of God. the correlate is God his Father, and the Foundation of this Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is Regeneration. But here a Chriſtian is not conſidered as any ways related to a Church, but only as realted to God, and who is not able to underſtand a Chriſtian as well as <hi>Adam</hi> to be a Son of God without any Relation to any Society of men what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>But ſince it is certain that God hath exerted this Regenerating Power to more than one, and that he hath many Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, hence it is that every Son of God ſtands in an other Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that is to all the reſt that are in the ſame manner born of God, which in conjunction make up Gods family or Church.</p>
            <p>But them I ſay, that the Church here is to be taken for the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church for the Father or Head of this Family is the inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41103:7"/>God, and the Children are Members who conſidered as to their Regeneration, that is the Foundation of the Relation are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo inviſible; and therefore neither in this ſence can the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be true, for every Chriſtian upon the account of his internal Memberſhip is not therefore a Member of a viſible Church, for there may be 7000 ſuch inviſible Members in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when there was no appearance of a viſible Church as to them, where any external Communion was held; and yet this is that the Propoſition drives at, that every Chriſtian as ſuch, is a Member of ſuch a Church with which external Communion may be held, which is in this ſence apparently falſe.</p>
            <p>Yet again all theſe internal Members of God's Family, may be conſidered as outwardly profeſſing their Faith and aſſociateing together as they can, for the Worſhip of God: among whom creep in many Hypocrites, by profeſſing the ſame Faith and joyning in the ſame Worſhip with them, which together make up the Catholick Viſible Church, in this ſence I grant that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry profeſſing Chriſtian may be reckoned as a Member of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick viſible Church.</p>
            <p>But yet I deny, that this relation is eſſential and neceſſary to him, upon the very account of his being a Chriſtian; for he might be a Believer and a Son of God, and internally related to all inviſible Members without this Catholick viſible Memberſhip, nor doth he indeed deny it, for in caſe (ſays he) that no ſuch vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church can be found, or in caſe they be ſcattered by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Perſecution, or in caſe of an unjuſt excommunication, Chriſtians may be Chriſtians without being members of Chriſts viſible Church, which indeed are conceſſions that overturn the Truth of his Propoſition; for if a man may be a Chriſtian with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being a Member of Chriſts viſible Church, then it can not be true that every Chriſtian upon the very account of his being ſo, is a Member of ſuch a Church: for if it be true that <hi>Peter</hi> may be a man without being incorporated into any civil Society, then it muſt be falſe to ſay, that <hi>Peter</hi> upon the very account of his being a man muſt be a member of ſuch a Society.</p>
            <p>But let us now come to examine the other part of the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and his ſence of it; which is what may be there meant by the Church of Chriſt, of which he ſaith, every Chriſtian upon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41103:7"/>the very account of his being ſo, is a member; and that he is bound to joyn with it in external Communion. By Church (as may be gathered out of his explication of this Propoſition) he underſtands <hi>a Society of particular Perſons, gathered out of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind and formed into a Body Politick of which Chriſt is the Head.</hi> This I confeſſe is ſomewhat, but not ſufficient to give us his deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate ſence thereof, for as he hath here deſcribed it, for ought we know, he may mean only an internal inviſible Church, which is an internal inviſible body Politick, of which the inviſible Chriſt is Head, and thoſe that are internally united to him by a true and living Faith, are inviſible Members. This certainly is an inviſible Church, for not only the Head is inviſible as to us, but ſo likewiſe are the Members conſidered as true Believers, for no man can ſee the Truth of anothers Faith clearly and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly.</p>
            <p>But methinks he ſhould not take [Church] in this ſence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe firſt, he ſpeaks of a Church wherewith every Chriſtian is bound to ſeek external Communion, but no external Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can be had with a Church conſidered as inviſible. And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, becauſe he ſpeaks of Communion with ſuch a Church where Communion is hazardous, as is implyed by his ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition <hi>(if it can be had,)</hi> now certainly there is no hazard in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining an internal Communion with Chriſt the Head and all true Believers, for that may always be had when an external Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion cannot.</p>
            <p>But if he by Church means the Catholick viſible Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of all individual profeſſors of the Chriſtian Doctrine thoroughout the world, united to Chriſt their Head, which is moſt likely to be his meaning, then the ſence of the Propoſition is this,</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Chriſt the inviſible Head in Heaven, being joyned to his inviſible Profeſſors on Earth make up a Body Politick (whether he will call this Body Politick viſible or inviſible I know not, but ſure I am, the Head thereof which is the more principal part in inviſible.) But this he ſaith, that it is the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of every particular Chriſtian to joyn with this Church in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Communion if it may be had.</p>
            <p>To this I ſay, it is well he puts in (if it may be had) for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41103:8"/>reaſon beſides what he imagined when he inſerted that clauſe, and that is, becauſe no ſuch Communion external can be had with ſuch a body Politick as he calls it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe it is very improper to ſay that any one is obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to hold an external Communion with a Politick body, where no Head is owned but what is inviſible; for ſince the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal and eſſential Member of a body Politick is the Head, and that no external Communion can be had therewith as inviſible, it cannot be truely ſaid that we may have, or are bound to ſeek ſuch an Eternal Communion therewith as a body politick. I wonder who ever talkt at that rate, as to ſay every man as a Creature was bound to ſeek an external Communion with man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, as making up a body Politick under the inviſible God the Creator and ſupream Governour.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſay no ſuch external Communion can be had, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the vaſt numbers of profeſſing Chriſtians ſcattered at ſuch great diſtances upon the face of the Earth, that no ſuch Communion can poſſibly be obtained, ſo that it is as poſſible to conceive how an external Communion may be had by every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual man with all mankind, as how it may be had by every Chriſtian with the whole body of Chriſtians throughout the World:</p>
            <p>This is ſo evident that he cannot but confeſs ſo much pag. 14. we cannot (ſaith he) Communicate with the Catholick Church, but by Communicating with ſome part of it.</p>
            <p>But I ſay, by Communicating with ſome part of it, we do not therefore Communicate externally with the whole, for who ever ſaid that a man by holding a Communion with one City or Corporation that thereby he held an external Politick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with all mankind, and what is it that you can ſay for the one, but I can ſay much alike for the other.</p>
            <p>Do you ſay, but all Chriſtians are united under one Head the Lord Chriſt, ſo (ſay I) are all mankind united under one God who is their Head and Governour.</p>
            <p>Do (you ſay) all Chriſtians Communicate in ſome external priviledges, ſo (ſay I) do all mankind, they are enlightned by the ſame Sun, breath in the ſame air, feed on the Fruits of the ſame Earth.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:41103:8"/>
            <p>Do you ſay, but they have not the ſame Laws as Chriſtians have, which are neceſſary to unite them in one body Politick. I anſwer, but if all mankind had the very ſame Laws, yet if the publication and execution of thoſe Laws were in different Kings hands that had juriſdiction over each other, this were not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſpeak them all of one external Politick Communion; no more do the ſame Laws amongſt Chriſtians (ſince the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and execution thereof, is in the hands of different viſible Church Governours, that have no juriſdiction over each other) ſpeak any external Politick Communion among all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
            <p>Thus have I ſhewn, of what words and phraſes, of an uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and undetermin'd ſence, the parts of the Propoſition conſiſt, and how hard it is, to give any tollerable ſound ſence of the whole; we ſhall now further enquire of the interpretation gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, whether it can afford any further light to underſtand it better.</p>
            <p>For the clearing of this (he ſaith) <hi>you may be pleaſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that the primary deſign and intention of our Saviour in his undertaking for us, was, not to ſave particular Perſons without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to a Society, but to gather to himſelf a Church in the form of a Body Politick, of which himſelf is the Head, and particular Chriſtians the Members, and in this method through obedience to his Laws and Government to bring men to Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I underſtand the force of theſe words with reſpect to the Propoſition, it is this that you would prove; that every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian upon the very account of his being ſo, muſt needs be a Member of the Church, becauſe Chriſt intended not to ſave particular Chriſtians but under the conſideration of being Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church.</p>
            <p>I confeſs if this was as true as I ſuſpect it to be falſe, there would be weight in what is ſaid: But let it be tryed.</p>
            <p>You ſay that Chriſt primarily deſigned to ſave his Church, and but ſecondarily individual Chriſtians, as incorporated in this Church.</p>
            <p>I pray tell me, do you take Church here, as you do in the Propoſition? certainly you ought ſo to do; why elſe do you call this a clearing of that? now it is evident you take Church
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41103:9"/>in the Propoſition, for the Catholick viſible Church exiſting in the World, with whom you ſay an external Communion is to be ſought, as hath been before ſhew'd. But how abſurd is what you ſay if you take Church in this ſence! For,</p>
            <p>Firſt, you hereby ſay that Chriſt did primarily deſign to ſave this preſent exiſting Catholick Church; what can be more abſurd? did not Chriſt, think you, as primarily deſign all thoſe parts of his Church that in their paſt Generations did once exiſt here on Earth, and doth not he alike deſign to ſave that part that is yet to be born? Again, you herein ſay, that Chriſt primarily deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſave the Catholick viſible Church, which is evidently falſe; for Chriſt never deſigned to ſave his viſible Catholick Church, much leſſe conſidered as viſible, and therefore cannot be ſaid Primarily to deſign Their Salvation: for Chriſts deſign was to ſave only a part of his viſible Church, and that part not conſidered as viſible, but as inviſibly united to himſelf by a liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Faith.</p>
            <p>Yet again if the quite contrary be true, <hi>viz.</hi> That Chriſt firſt deſigned the Salvation of particular Chriſtians and but in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condary ſence the Church that is made up of them, then what you ſay muſt needs be falſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that Chriſt deſigned Salvation to the Church primarily, and to particular Members ſecondarily, as in Union with the Church. The former of which I affect for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe all individual ſincere Chriſtians have all qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation, antecedently to a viſible Church ſtate, as actual Faith and Repentance if they be adult; or the promiſe of the Covenant upon their Parents Faith if they be Infants, which are Foundations of, and give Title to a viſible Church State. Therefore our Saviour primarily deſigned to ſave them as ſuch, and as for his deſigning ſuch to be admitt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into a viſible. Church State by Baptiſm, it was but to Seal that Salvation to them, and to promote and carry on that Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation that was antecedently ſecured to them by the Covenant, upon their Repentance and Faith in the Lord Jeſus: the very Truth is, Chriſt did not intend at all to ſave men as viſible Church Members, but only as true Believers, for the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental ſaving Doctrine of the Goſpel doth not run thus, he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41103:9"/>that is a Member of the viſible Church ſhall be ſaved, <hi>but he that Believeth ſhall be ſaved, and he that Believeth not ſhall be damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be objected, But doth not the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> Preach not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Repentance, but likewiſe Baptiſm as neceſſary to Remiſſion of ſins; and conſequently to Salvation: when he ſays Repent and be Baptized every one of you, for the Remiſſion of ſins? And is not Baptiſme an Ordinance of admiſſion into a viſible Church State?<note place="margin">Acts 2.30.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I anſw. they are both indeed commanded, but not as equally ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, for Repentance gives the fundamental title to remiſſion, Baptiſme doth only give the Seal; the former is ſo neceſſary that without it no remiſſion can be obtained: the other is but for the more comfortable aſſurance of that priviledge to the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; but not abſolutely neceſſary as the other: and this our Saviour moſt clearly intimates when he ſaith, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>He that Believeth and is Baptized, ſhall be ſaved; but he that Believeth not ſhall be damned.</hi> Men ſhall be damned meerly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of their unbelief, and not meerly for want of Baptiſm, provided they have Faith. And yet Baptiſm hath its great uſe, as I have acknowledged, but as I ſaid not abſolutely neceſſary, for if men only Believe and never have an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of being Baptized, and ſo of being admitted into a viſible Church ſtate thereby, then Salvation is not at all hazarded.</p>
            <p>My next reaſon is this, It cannot be true that Chriſt only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to ſave particular Chriſtians as Members of the viſible Church: becauſe it were impoſſible then that any Chriſtians that were not viſible Church Members ſhould be ſaved, for if it muſt fare with particular Chriſtians, with reſpect to this body Politick (as he is pleaſed to call it) the Church, as it doth with the Members of the natural Body, where it is confeſt that God by his Providence only intends to give life to each Member, and likewiſe the continuance of Life as united together in one body, it will certainly follows that if any Member of the Church be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the Church it muſt neceſſarily periſh, as if a hand or a foot were ſeparated from the natural body it doth certainly periſh. But by his leave this is very falſe, as to particular Chriſtians with reſpect to the Church: for, firſt all Chriſtians
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41103:10"/>do not ſpring out of the Church as the Members of the natural body do out of that body, for when Infidels belive, they ſpring out of the World or Maſſe of mankind, and not out of the Church; and by believing are firſt united to Chriſt, and then as <hi>Saul</hi> converted, they eſſay to joyn themſelves to the Church, ſo that firſt they are internal members of a Church, or are fit matter to be made members of, and afterwards making a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, are made formal Members of a viſible Church, which is ſolemnized by Baptiſme. Secondly, and if it ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen that by unjuſt excommunication any true Chriſtian be cut off from the viſible Church, yet it keeps its Life, as no Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in a natural body can do. The concluſion is this, that if Chriſtians are in a ſalvable ſtate before Union to a viſible Church, and if they may be in a ſalvable ſtate, when wrongfully cut off by Excommunication; then it cannot be true, that Chriſt did but in a ſecondary way intend the Salvation of particular Chriſtians <hi>viz.</hi> as united to a Church.</p>
            <p>My third and laſt reaſon is this, I ſay Chriſt did not prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily deſign to ſave his Church, and but ſecondarily particular Members as he aſſerts: which I thus prove. That reſpect which individual men have to civil Society, as Kingdomes or Republicks; that reſpect have particular Chriſtians to the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church of Chriſt, according to his own notion of a Church which he conſiders as a body Politick. Now I ſay, God in mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the World, did not primarily deſign Kingdomes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths, but he primarily deſigned the giving of particular men their exiſtences: and ſecondarily, Kingdoms and Republicks for their better accommodation; Men were not made for King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, but Kingdoms for Men. Therefore ſo did Chriſt, he firſt deſigned the putting of particular men into a State of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by giving to them Faith and Repentance and Remiſſion of ſins, and then deſigned, as a conſequent thereof, to collect them into a Society or Societies, under Governours of his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be ruled by Laws of his own Ordination, for the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them up in their Faith and comforts to his Glory: ſo that this Society or Societies, of Church or Churches, with the Laws and Ordinances thereto belonging, are but for the ſakes and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinated to the welfare of particular Chriſtians, and therefore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41103:10"/>it is neceſſary that Chriſt ſhould firſt intend the welfare or Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of particulars, before the meer aſſociating them into Church or Churches under government, which is but a means to that great end of ſaving particulars. For certainly, that which is more excellent in the Nature of things, is primarily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by every rational Agent, before that which is leſſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: ſo certainly is the reſtauration of particular Perſons, in giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them renewed Natures, Remiſſion of ſins, and a Title to Salvation, before that meer order that ought to be amongſt them for their ſecurity and comfort, which is acquired by aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Church Government.</p>
            <p>If it yet be not clear, give me leave to illuſtrate this matter yet further by this ſimilitude: Let us conſider Chriſt as the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of an Army, who is by the Apoſtle called the Captain of our Salvation, and the Church under him as an Army under ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Officers, for their better Order and Government; and all particular Chriſtians as ſo many particular Souldiers. Now let us conſider the ſeveral ends which a general hath in gathering his Souldiers into an Army, and which end is more principally intended, and which end leſſe principally or ſubordinately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. His firſt end is to ſubdue his Enemies, to the Praiſe of his Juſtice and Valour: the next end intended is the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Souldiers, without which the more principal end can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be obtained; and that which is an end ſubordinate to both theſe, is the keeping his Souldiers in Union and Order under their ſeveral Officers, for without this Union and Order, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Souldiers cannot ſo well be preſerved: ſo that here it is evident that the uniting of his Men and keeping them under Diſcipline, is ſubordinately intended for the preſervation of particulars. In like manner God in Chriſt deſigning to ſave ſinners, Firſt, he intends the Praiſe of his Glorious Grace; Secondly, he intends the Salvation of particular ſinners, by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generating and pardoning of them: And laſtly, he intends the Collection of them into a body or bodies under Diſcipline, for their better ſafety and ſecurity; this laſt is not principally or leſſe principally, but that which is ſubordinately intended to both the other. The concluſion that ariſeth hence is this, that this Author is much miſtaken when he ſaith, that Chriſt did pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41103:11"/>intend the Salvation of his Church, and ſecondarily the Salvation of particular Chriſtians; <hi>cujus contrarium verum eſt;</hi> as I have ſhewed.</p>
            <p>We ſhall now further conſider what he hath ſaid for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this his nation, concerning Chriſts primary intention to ſave his Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is no more than what is the ſence and Language of the Holy Scriptures, wherein, whatever Chriſt is ſaid to have done and ſuffered for mankind, he is ſaid to have done for them, not as ſcattered individuals, but as incorporated into a Church. Thus Chriſt ſav'd the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.25. Act. 20.25. Eph. 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>and gave himſelf for it. Chriſt Redeemed the Church with his own precious Blood. Chriſt is the Saviour of his Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The plain</hi> conſequence <hi>from hence</hi> is (ſaith he) that every <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſo far <hi>as he is</hi> a Chriſtian, ſo far he is a Member of the <hi>Church;</hi> and by virtue of that Relation to the Church it is, that he hath any Relation to Chriſt, or any Title to the Priviledges of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>I anſwer it is a wonder to me, to ſee the Authour, otherwiſe a Perſon of good abilities, ſo ſtrangely miſled into the confidence of a concluſion that is raiſed upon ſuch palpable miſtaken prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipals.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He ſays that what ever Chriſt hath done and ſuffered for man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, he hath done it for them; not as ſcattered individuals, but as incorporated into a Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I perceive by this that the Authour is not for Univerſal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, as ſome of his brethren are; for I cannot ſee how Chriſt dying for all, is conſiſtent with Chriſt's dying for men, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as incorporated into his Church, for it is certain, that the greateſt number of individuals that hath been, or are in the World, were, or are not like to be ſo incorporated. Yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, certainly the Author doth run himſelf and his Reader into much confuſion for want of a Regular ſtating of the ſeveral Aſpects, which Chriſts ſufferings have to mankind, as they fall under divers conſiderations. As firſt, if mankind be conſidered as lapſed into a ſtate of ſin and death: ſo they are ſaid to be Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to God and Righteouſneſs, Dead in Treſpaſſes and ſins, without God, without hope. I hope the Author doth not take
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41103:11"/>men ſo conſidered as in any Church ſtate, and yet it is certain that according to Scriptures, Chriſts: ſuffering was with Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to men as ſuch, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. <hi>God commendeth his Love towards us, in that while we were yet ſinners Chriſt died for us.</hi> So <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21. <hi>And you that were ſometime alienated and Enemies in your mind by wicked works, yet now hath he reconciled in the Body of his Fleſh through Death.</hi> In theſe Texts it's evident that Chriſt's death, reſpected men as incoporated in the corrupt Maſſe of mankind; and not as incorporated into a Church.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Chriſts ſufferings reſpects men, conſidered as ſuch, that <hi>de futuro,</hi> were to partake of the benefits of Chriſt's Death: which benefits, are either of an abſolute, or of a Relative and Politick Conſideration.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that are abſolute, are ſuch as the changing of mens Natures, Remiſſion of Sins, Faith in Chriſt, Repentance from dead Work; theſe are all given and beſtowed on en with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to what Chriſt did and ſuffered for them. Here men are to be conſidered abſolutely as individual Chriſtians, and not as any members of a Society or a Church, for I can, as any man elſe may eaſily, conſider a man as a Believer, as a Penitent, as in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with God, without conſidering him under any Politick Relations: as we may conceive of men as wiſe, juſt and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, without conceiving them as Citizens or Subjects. There are other benefits that are likewiſe the purchaſe of Chriſts death, and they are of a relative and Politick conſideration; and here it is that the Communion of the Saints, or church Fellow-ſhip hath its place, which Communion is either internal, and this is a priviledge peculiar only to that Church of Chriſt, which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Member is conſidered as really and ſincerely united to Chriſt; by a true Faith: and to each other in a love unfeigned, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal; which properly belongs to Chriſtians co-united together in an external profeſſion of Faith, in aſſociating for publick worſhip and ſubmitting to Chriſts Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>Now of all theſe benefits, ſome are more principall, ſome leſs, ſome are of abſolute neceſſity to Salvation; others not.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that are of a more principal conſideration, and of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity to Salvation; are ſuch that belong to Chriſtians as individuals, ſuch as Faith and Repentance, Remiſſion of ſins,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41103:12"/>and ſuch like, which they have by virtue of Union with Chriſt, without any reſpect to any Politick Union with one another: as for thoſe benefits which are of a Politick or relative conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, they are leſſe principal and not of that neceſſity to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſuch are the Love of all Saints and their mutual Prayers for each other. Such are worſhiping together, and the benefits of Chriſts Diſcipline, now though theſe are excellent in their kinds, yet much inferiour to thoſe of Faith and Repentance and Remi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion of ſins, as being not ſo abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation, as theſe are.</p>
            <p>Now I would fain know of the Author, whether it be more true to ſay, that Chriſt by his death did primarily intend to ſave men as Believers, as Penitent, as Renewed and pardoned, which belongs to Chriſtians conſidered as individuals, which is what I affirm: or to ſay he primarily intended to ſave men as hearing, praying, praiſing and receiving the Lords Supper to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and likewiſe by being under Diſcipline; which are the priviledges that belong to Chriſtians as falling under a Politick conſideration: which is what he ſeems to affirm. If the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer be true, then the latter which he hath aſſerted is falſe; for both of them cannot be primarily intended. Now I conceive the former true, becauſe it is every where affirmed in Scripture, that he that believes, he that repents, he that is regenerate, he that is pardoned, ſhall be ſaved.</p>
            <p>But it is no where promiſed, that thoſe that pray and praiſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with the Church, that they ſhall be ſaved, except it be with reſpect unto Faith and Repentance, which as I have ſaid, belong to Chriſtians as individuals, and not as Members of a Church.</p>
            <p>But he ſaith, <hi>that herein he ſpeaks but the ſence and Language of the Holy Scriptures:</hi> and here he quoteth three texts, as <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.23. well! what doth he gather thence? <hi>Hence</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it is plain, that Chriſt died primarily for his Church, and for individuals not as ſcattered but as incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated into his Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by your favour here is more in your concluſion, than is in thoſe premiſed Texts: indeed I read there, that Chriſt gave himſelf for his Church, and that he redeemed his Church with his blood, and that he is the Saviour of his body which is his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41103:12"/>Church. But I find not a word there, of dying primarily for his Church, and but ſecondarily for individuals as incorporated into his Church.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall ſay, all this is implyed if not expreſt. I ſay, who ever ſo thinks is obliged to ſhew how, and which way it comes to be implied, but to ſave them the Labour, I am bold to affirm the contrary, that there is no ſuch thing implyed; my reaſon is this, becauſe Church in each of thoſe places is taken for a collection of particular Chriſtians, conſidered primarily as true believers, as true penitents, and but ſecondarily as in Union one with another, and as in Fellowſhip in Church Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</p>
            <p>My reaſons are, firſt becauſe there is nothing in the words or context that can force a contrary interpretation. Secondly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the nature of the thing ſpoken of in theſe verſes will bear no interpretation, but ſuch as I give. Becauſe the intents of Chriſts dying muſt be meaſured according to the Nature of things, ſo that what is more excellent muſt be intended before that which is leſſe excellent, now mens being particularly uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Chriſt by Faith, their having their Natures changed, and their ſins pardoned, are more excellent than their Union and Communion with each other in external Ordinances, that are but inferior Miniſteries ſubſervient to their Faith, and their renewed Natures, and the edification of them therein; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt muſt intend his death primarily for his Church as Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers: now as I have formerly ſaid, Believers, as ſuch, are not Members of a Church, for Faith ſpeaks a relation to Chriſt, but no relation immediately to any other Chriſtian or Chriſtians whatever.</p>
            <p>Again under what qualification, and for what reaſon Chriſt is ſaid primarily to be Saviour of the Church, his body; under that qualification, and for that reaſon, Chriſt is ſaid primarily to dye and ſhed his blood for his Body. But Chriſt doth not ſave his Church under the qualification, or for that reaſon primarily, becauſe they are united in external Acts of Worſhip and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and upon that account it is they are of your viſible Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick body or Church, but becauſe its particular Members are Believers and penitent, but Chriſtians <hi>quatenus</hi> Believers or
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41103:13"/>penitent are not conſider as Members of a Church, for indeed Faith and Repentance ſpeak no relation immediately to any but God and Chriſt, that of Church Memberſhip comes in as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent thereof, to which priviledge Faith gives the Title. Therefore Chriſt did not dye to ſave his Church <hi>quatenus</hi> a Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, united for worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but <hi>quatenus</hi> its Members are true Believers and no further, and for this cauſe I aſſert, that the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary end of Chriſts death was to ſave individual Believers and but ſecondarily to ſave his Church, ſo far as it conſiſted of ſuch and no further.</p>
            <p>Yet again if Chriſt intended primarily to ſave men becauſe they were Members of a Church: Then certainly, the firſt thing that the Goſpel ſhould preſſe upon ſinners is, that they ſhould firſt unite themſelves to the Church, which to ſay it doth is both falſe and abſurd: its falſe, for the firſt cry of the Goſpel is to men conſidered in a ſtate of ſin and Death, and it is that they would repent of their ſins and believe in the Lord Jeſus, upon the doing of which it promiſeth remiſſion and a Title to Salvation, and till this be done there is no mention of any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand obliging them to become a Member of a Church: and reality or profeſſion, men are no more capable of being Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of a Church, than a Hog or Horſe are capable of being Citizens of <hi>London.</hi> He that conſiders what hath been ſaid, may ſoon ſee what little help thoſe Scriptures he mentions afford his notion, and upon what ſlender grounds he builds that confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent concluſion of his, <hi>viz. That by virtue of that relation to the Church it is that a Chriſtian hath any relation to Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He addes, <hi>Agreeable to this notion, it is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>very plain, that Baptiſm which is by all acknowledged to be the Ceremony of initiating us into Chriſtianity, is in Scripture declared to be the Rite, whereby we are entred and admitted into the Church,</hi> this St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly tells us, <hi>That we are all Baptized into one Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> again <hi>that Chriſt hath ſanctified,</hi> i. e. hath <hi>ſeparated his Church by the waſhing of Water, and the Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wonder that the Author ſhould ſay that theſe Scriptures are agreeable to his notion, that Chriſt intends the Salvation of no particular Chriſtians but conſidered as members of a Church.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:41103:13"/>
            <p>I anſwer, they are ever juſt ſo much agreeable to his notion as the texts before-named.</p>
            <p>He ſays all acknowledge, that <hi>Baptiſme is a ceremony initiat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us into chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wonder who acknowledges ſo in your ſence? I am ſure not all or but very few: for Chriſtianity objectively is the doctrine of Chriſt ſubjectively the ſame Doctrine as believed by us with a reſolution to obey it, but aſſuredly the Doctrine of Chriſt is firſt preached and heard and believed, and a reſolution taken up to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it, and all this is antecedent in the adult to baptiſme, or ought to be ſo. As for Baptiſme, it is but a profeſſing ſign of my being a Chriſtian, or a ſeal of the promiſes that God hath made to me, as ſuch, and is not a Ceremony that makes me a Chriſtian, or gives me my Chriſtianity. <hi>Abraham</hi> was a Believer, and a Friend of God, and juſtified by his faith antecedent to circumciſion, and ſo are the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> they are believers, friends of God, juſtified by their Faith in Chriſt, antecedent to Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>But it is added, <hi>doth not</hi> Paul <hi>ſay we are all by one Spirit bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into one body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True, he doth ſo; But I deny your conſequence thence dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that therefore Chriſt died primarily for his Church, and but ſecondarily for the individual members thereof, or that we have primarily a relation to the Church and but ſecondarily to Chriſt, <hi>i.e.</hi> by virtue of the former relation. There is not one word or ſyllable in the text tending that way. For Firſt, what is there in theſe words, <hi>we are baptized into one body,</hi> to ſignifie a priority of our relation to the Church, any more than in thoſe <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. where it is ſaid <hi>we are baptized into Chriſt,</hi> to ſignifie a priority of our relation to Chriſt, and by him to his Church? reconcile theſe if you can to the ſence of your conſequence, and give us ſome evident reaſon why we muſt needs underſtand, that thereby is meant we are baptized into the Church primarily, and into Chriſt ſecondarily: But I ſhall be bold to tell you ſuch an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation is evidently abſurd, as is manifeſt in ſeveral inſtances in other kind of relations. Whoever ſaid that King <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d was only related to <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, as he is related to his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> and the reſt of the Royal Family? cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly as he is the Elder Brother his relation to his Father was
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41103:14"/>firſt both in nature and time to any relation he ſtood in to his younger brethren. Or whoever ſaid that the individuals of a Kingdome cannot be conſidered in relation to their King and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign antecedently to their being conſidered as fellow ſubjects? when certainly the relation of fellow ſubjects doth ariſe upon the ſuppoſed relation of thoſe individuall ſubjects to their ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign; for the formal reaſon why you and I are fellow ſubjects is, becauſe we are individually related to the ſame King, and therefore relation to him is antecedent to our relation to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as ſubjects.</p>
            <p>The ſence of this text now urged, ſo far as I underſtand is only this, that all that are baptized upon a juſt title are ſuppoſed to partake of the ſanctifying operation of the Spirit, of which the waſhing of the water of baptiſme is a ſign, by which they are declared to be animated by one and the ſelf-ſame Spirit, as all the living members of Chriſt are, and conſequently that they are one with them, and that therefore they ought all of them to be both internally and externally as uſefull and helpfull to each other as poſſibly they can; But how you can draw ſuch a concluſion hence that therefore theſe individuals are no ways related to Chriſt but as they are thus united to one another I cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand for the reaſons before given.</p>
            <p>The other text is <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.22. where it is ſaid, <hi>that Chriſt hath ſanctified</hi> (or ſeparated) <hi>his Church by the waſhing of water and the word,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Very well! what of this? we grant you, that every Church member, if adult, is converted by the word, and afterward (if it may be) ought to be baptized; upon this account it is ſaid that the Church is ſeparated by water and the word, becauſe all its individual members are, or ought to be ſo converted and bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. Therefore ſaith he, every individual Chriſtian is ſaved as incorporated into the Church. I deny the conſequence, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion by the word is antecedent to Baptiſme or to a Viſible Church State, and of it ſelf gives a title to Salvation, though never any ſuch viſible Church ſtate by baptiſme follows; But if Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme follows, I ſay again, Chriſtians are not ſaved primarily as baptized and as externally Church members, but primarily as true believers and internally united to Chriſt. And certainly a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41103:14"/>believer, as ſuch, ſpeaks no neceſſary relation to any Church or viſible ſociety whatever, and therefore it could not poſſibly be the Apoſtles intendment in that place, or the other, to ſignifie that Chriſtians had no relation to Chriſt, or ſaving intereſt in him but what they derived from a participation of Baptiſme and a conjunction with a viſible Church,</p>
            <p>Having thus finiſhed his proof, that all Chriſtians are members of the catholick viſible Church: he proceeds to the proof of the ſecond part of the propoſition, which is, <hi>that therefore every Chriſtian is bound to joyn in external communion with the ſaid Church.</hi> This he thinks is clear upon <hi>two reaſons,</hi> Firſt becauſe <hi>without ſuch a conjunction the ends of Church ſociety cannot be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, which ends are the ſolemn worſhip of God, the publick pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our religion, and the mutual edification one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Becauſe without ſuch a conjunction in external com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Catholick viſible Church, we cannot be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the benefits and priviledges that Chriſt hath made over to the members of his Church, ſuch are the pardon of ſin, and the grace of the holy Spirit,</hi> and ſo he concludes, <hi>we have no promiſes of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Graces but of thoſe means, ſo that in order to the partaking of them, there is an abſolute neceſſity laid upon us, of joyning and communicating with the Church.</hi> Thus far he.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, firſt, whereas he ſays that he <hi>hath made it evident, that every Chriſtian, upon the account of his very being ſo, a member of the catholick viſible Church,</hi> that I have already denied, and upon what grounds and reaſons I have denied it is before ſhewn, as for his conſequence that <hi>therefore every Chriſtian is bound upon the very account of his being ſo, to joyn with the Church catholick vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in external communion:</hi> That I have alſo denyed and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why I have ſhewed, as Firſt, there is no ſuch external com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion to be had with that vaſt body as the catholick Church is, beſides if there were, it might be unlawfull, becauſe if commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion could not be had but upon ſinfull conditions, or without a manifeſt hazard of my ſalvation, or in caſe one were wrongful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excommunicated, there is in theſe caſes no obligation on a Chriſtian as ſuch to any ſuch external communion, but a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian may be ſtill a Chriſtian without it.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41103:15"/>But let us ſee how he proves his conſequence: His firſt reaſon is, <hi>becauſe without ſuch a conjunction the ends of Church ſociety cannot be had, which are ſolemn worſhip and mutual Edification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> What? not without a conjunction with the catholick viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church? certainly meetings for ſolemn worſhip and mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Edification are not terms wherein Chriſtians hold communion with the catholick viſible Church, for they are proper only to particular worſhiping congregations. I wonder in what Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies do the Chriſtians in <hi>England,</hi> and the Chriſtians in <hi>Preſtor Johns</hi> country meet for ſolemn worſhip and mutual Edification? I know he thinks the matter if ſalved, by telling us, that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans meeting in any congregation in <hi>England,</hi> for worſhip and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Edification, do thereby hold externall communion in thoſe things with the whole Church throughout the world. But <hi>I</hi> conceive this will not ſerve his turn, without the could equally i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine how a man by holding communion with the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> might be ſaid thereby to hold a civil external communion with all mankind, which I think is ſo wild a conceit as no man yet ever aſſerted, for he muſt remember he is ſpeaking of ſuch an external communion that is proper to a politick viſible Body, to the conſtituting of which kind of communion it is not enough to have the ſame laws, the ſame cuſtomes, no nor the ſame kind of ſolemn meetings for worſhip, to ſpeak all viſible Chriſtians to be of the ſame external politick communion; for ſuppoſe in <hi>France</hi> they had the ſame laws and cuſtoms, the ſame kind of officers, as Conſtables, Juſtices, Parliament, and a King, as we have in <hi>England,</hi> and all under the Government of the very ſame invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible God, it doth not follow ſo long as there is no dependance of theſe Kingdomes each on the other, that therefore the people of <hi>England</hi> are of the ſame external politick communion with thoſe in <hi>France.</hi> Yea further, though theſe two Kingdoms may mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in times of peace adviſe with each other for their mutual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, and in caſe of differences betwixt them, they may forbid trading or converſe with each other, which is a kind of civil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, yet for all this they may not be ſaid to be of the ſame external civil politick communion, and why? becauſe their reſpective Magiſtrates are independent and have no juriſdiction over each other. Upon the very ſame ground I deny any ſuch thing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41103:15"/>as an external Politick Communion betwixt the Members of the Catholick Church: for though they have all the ſame Laws, the ſame Sacraments, the ſame kind of ſolemn meetings for Worſhip, and all under the ſame kind of viſible Governours, and all this under the ſame inviſible Head the Lord Jeſus, though ſo far as they can, and the diſtances of places will admit) they may adviſe with each other for their mutual good, and in caſe that any prove Hereticks they may, ſo far as may be, diſown or refuſe Communion, as in the inſtances before ſaid, yet all this no more proves them to be of the ſame external Politick communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than the like agreements might ſpeak the Kingdom of <hi>France</hi> and that of <hi>England</hi> of the ſame politick civil communion, and why? but becauſe Chriſt hath left no viſible politick Head to have juriſdiction over the reſt.</p>
            <p>If you ſay this notion ſpeaks a good word for the Headſhip of the Pope.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, no ſuch matter, for there is no need of ſuch a Head, nor of any ſuch external Politick Communion in the Church no more than in the World, God hath well enough Governed the World without any ſuch Univerſal civil Monarch, and doth as well govern the Church without any ſuch Univerſal vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Head.</p>
            <p>And now let us ſee what of force then is in his ſecond reaſon, which is this, ſuch a conjunction in external Communion with he Catholick viſible Church is neceſſary, <hi>elſe we cannot poſſibly partake of the priviledges that Chriſt hath made over to this his Church, as the Remiſſion of Sins, and the Graces of the Holy Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, He ſays that Chriſt hath made over the priviledges of pardon of ſin and the Graces of his Spirit to the Church pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily, and that before any particular perſon can partake of pardon of Sin and the Graces of the Spirit, he muſt joyn with the Church in external Communion. But how abſurd is all this! by Church he here means the Catholick viſible Church, but I wonder how it can be truly ſaid, that pardon of ſin, or the Graces of the Spirit can be ſaid to be made over to the viſible Church, as priviledges, when as it is very certain that Chriſt never made over ſuch priviledges to the Church as viſible?</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:41103:16"/>
            <p>But I perceive he underſtands it miniſterially, that is to ſay, that a man is pardoned, or partake of the Graces of the Spirit, but by the Miniſtry of the Church: well! let this be granted what will thence follow? I am ſure that will not follow which you ſay doth follow, that therefore we muſt firſt be made Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church before we can be pardoned or ſanctifyed by the Spirit: for ſuppoſe the Church meets for ſolemn worſhip, and the miniſter is Preaching, and there comes in one or more Infidels for curioſity to ſee and hear, I hope you will not ſay that theſe Infidels becauſe they are in the ſame place with the Church, that therefore they are joyned as Members with the Church; ſuppoſe now theſe Infidels are by the Sermon convinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and perfectly converted to a true Faith in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I now demand, Theſe men that thus are converted, do they believe without or with the Grace of the Spirit? again ſo ſoon as they have believed, are they pardoned or are they not? I ſay they could not have believed without the Grace of the Spirit, and that ſo ſoon as they truly believed they were pardoned: and you dare not (I think) ſay the contrary. Now I pray you is not this Grace of the Spirit, and pardoning of ſin Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated before theſe men were joyned to the Church as viſible Members. How then can you ſay that men are obliged to joyn with the Church as Members, elſe they have neither Grace nor pardon? the very Truth is, the primary reaſon of Chriſts inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of viſible Church Memberſhip, was not for the giving of the firſt Grace of the Spirit, or giving pardon, but it was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed as a means of conveying further degrees of Grace, and clearer aſſurance of pardon viſible Church Memberſhip doth ſuppoſe the Grace of converſion (in the adult) and pardon, but doth not give or Communicate it.</p>
            <p>I had now done with his firſt Propoſition, but that for two inferences he draws from a conſideration of the whole; as firſt (ſaith he) <hi>therefore their poſition is untrue, who maintain that our obligation to Church Communion ariſeth from a voluntary admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſelves into ſome particular congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſay, notwithſtanding all he hath ſaid that poſition may be true, for he hath been all this while ſpeaking of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal viſible Church. But they that hold that poſition, maintain
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41103:16"/>it only with reſpect to a particular Church, and I hope there is no contradiction, for one that believes and is Baptized to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſarily a Member of the Univerſal Church, and yet to be volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily a Member either of particular Worſhiping Congregation either in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His ſecond deduction is as wild, <hi>for</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hence we may ſee how extravagantly they diſcourſe that talk of Chrſtianity at large, without relation to a Church or Communion with a Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I ſay is ſtrangely inferred, as if we could not diſcourſe of men, as men, without relation to Cities or Kingdoms, and certainly we may with a very good reaſon ſometimes diſcourſe of Chriſtians, as Chriſtians, without relation to any Church whether particular or Univerſal, and this without any <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His ſecond Propoſition.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>That every one is bound to joyn in Communion with the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed national Church to which he belongs, ſuppoſing there be nothing in the Terms of its Communion that renders it unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for him ſo to do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>is plain, becauſe external Communion cannot be had with the Catholick Church but by externally Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nionicating with ſome part of it.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>To this I have already anſwered, that there is no ſuch thing as an external Politick Communion to be had with the Catholick Church neither immediately which himſelf confeſſeth, no nor mediately by Communicating with ſome part of it, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive I have made evident in my anſwer to the former Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
            <p>But in caſe any ſuch Communion could be had immediately or mediately, yet I would have it remembred, that this ſort of Communion is not to be ſought by every Chriſtian upon the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry account of his being ſo, but upon the account of his being a viſible profeſſing Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>And how let us come to ſome Iſſue, we will grant you that every Chriſtian, conſidered as viſible, ought to endeavour to joyn
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41103:17"/>with ſome part of the Catholick viſible Church, for publick Worſhip and the edification of himſelf and others, but why this particular Church muſt be national, I do not underſtand, I am ſure there is no need it ſhould be national, for I do as truly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my ſelf to be a viſible Member of the Catholick viſible Church, by joyning in external Communion with one ſingle viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Congregation, as if I was united a Member to a National Church. But in very Truth, I do much doubt whether any ſuch thing is to be had as an external Communion with a National Church, any more than with the Catholick viſible Church: for you place <hi>the Acts of external Communion to conſiſt in meeting together in ſolemn worſhip, and in mutual Edification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I would fain know where any Nation of Chriſtians do meet together for ſolemn Worſhip, true if you could find any Nation of Chriſtians that did often meet at one place to Worſhip God, and to rejoyce before the Lord together, as the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> uſed to do when they came up to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to keep the Feaſts of the Lord, I ſhould not ſtick to call ſuch a National Church uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted external Communion, but to ſpeak of a joyning with a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church of Chriſtians in external Communion, where Millions of the Members of the ſuppoſed National Church, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver perhaps came nigh one the other for ſcores of Miles, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſo as to Hear, or Pray, or receive the Supper together, or to Edifie each other, is to talk without any ſolid ground.</p>
            <p>If you ſay, but if we joyn with any one Worſhipping Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation in external Communion, we do thereby joyn with the whole Nation of Chriſtians in external Communion.</p>
            <p>If you ſay ſo, I think you ſay more than you can prove, for I do not underſtand that becauſe I Worſhip God with a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation in <hi>London,</hi> that therefore I Worſhip God with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation at <hi>York.</hi> True, by my Worſhipping at <hi>London</hi> I do declare my ſelf to be of the ſame Faith with thoſe that Worſhip at <hi>York,</hi> and I am therefore bound to account of them as my brethren, and ſo to love and Pray for them as ſuch, by which means an internal Communion is maintained as among Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that are ſuppoſed and hoped to be united to Chriſt, but yet I am to ſeek how this external Communion can be had, when perhaps we ſhall never ſee each other as long as we live.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:41103:17"/>
            <p>If you ſay that all the Chriſtians in a Nation may hold an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Communion in being all under one Diſcipline, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement whereof being depoſited in the hands of one viſible Head, as was the High Prieſt to the Church of the Jews.</p>
            <p>This indeed were ſomething, if it could be proved that Jeſus Chriſt did ever appoint ſuch an Officer for the Government of all his Diſciples in each Nation, but if it be made to appear that all Miniſters or Paſtors of particular Worſhiping Congregations, have equal Power to Govern their reſpective Churches, and that they have no Power of juriſdiction one over another, and that there is no inſtituted Officers appointed by Chriſt Superior to them, with any Power of juriſdiction over them. Then I ſay, there can be no ſuch external Communion of all Chriſtians in a Nation under the juriſdiction of any ſuch High Prieſt, and that therefore there is no ſuch thing as a National Church of Chriſtians, wherewith an external communion can be held. You know well who they are that are for an equality of Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Power.</p>
            <p>Many more things may be ſaid of this matter, but I ſhall at preſent wave them, and proceed to conſider what he further ſaith.</p>
            <p>He hath already ſaid, that every Chriſtian ought to joyn in external Communion with a National Church, that thereby he might hold Communion with the Catholick. But preſently he ſtarts an Objection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But it may be ſaid, that there may be ſeveral diſtinct Churches in the place where we live, there may be the fixed regular Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the National Church, and there may be ſeparate Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, both which are or pretend to be parts of the Catholick Church, ſo that it may be all one as to our Communicating with that, which of theſe we joyn with, ſuppoſing we joyn but with one of them, and conſequently there is no neceſsity from that principle that we ſhould hold Communion with the Aſſemblies of the Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Church.</hi> So far he—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Very good! now let us ſee how he anſwers it, which part of the Argument in the Objection doth he deny? doth he deny ſuch ſeparate Congregations to be parts of the Catholick Church? or doth he deny that in joyning with any part of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41103:18"/>Catholick Church we thereby joyn with the whole? he denies neither: Then I ſay he grants the whole, for theſe two being granted, the concluſion follows, that they who joyn with thoſe ſeparate Congregations do thereby preſerve the Catholick Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and therefore there is no need of joyning with a National Church to attain the end propoſed, What ſaith he now? He ſeems not to deny this, but tells us <hi>that notwithſtanding if we ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate or refuſe Communion with them, that we do not preſerve the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Body, ſo far as in us lies, which the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Laws of Society, and the expreſſe precepts of Chriſtianity require of every Member.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I would now fain know of him what are thoſe Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Laws of Society, as ſuppoſe of Kingdomes or Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, that oblige its Subjects or Citizens to ſeek the Unity and Peace of thoſe Societies or Citizens to ſeek the Unity the known Laws of the ſaid Kingdoms; and the orders of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations regulated by the Charters granted by their Princes? but if any inferiour Officers of Kingdoms or Corporations, ſhall impoſe Laws upon the Subjects or Citizens, that are not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to, but rather ſeem contrary to the Laws of the Kingdom, and the Power granted in thoſe Charters, if ſuch Subjects or Citizens oppoſe and refuſe ſubjection, and will not communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate in thoſe things; who dare ſay that ſuch do not ſeek the Peace of Kingdoms and Corporations as much as in them lies? or as much as is fit?</p>
            <p>And let him likewiſe tell us what are thoſe expreſſe precepts of Chriſtianity, that oblige its Members any further to ſeek the Unity of the Church, than to believe, do, and obſerve thoſe things which Chriſt the Head of his Church hath commanded. Chriſtians then ſeek the Unity of the Body, (ſo far as in them lies,) when they ſeek it according to a Goſpel rule; for it doth not lye in their Power to ſeek it any other ways.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to ſeparate from Congregations with whom we may lawfully Communicate, is not to ſeek the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Body, ſo far as in us lies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is not univerſally true, for what if one ſhifteth his Habitation to another Pariſh, for the benefit of the Labours of a more pious Miniſter? here is a ſeparation from an eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41103:18"/>Aſſembly, and yet no breach upon the Unity of the Body.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe one ſtill abides in the Pariſh, and yet conſtantly Hears and Communicates with a Church of an other Pariſh, as I ſuppoſe ſome of your own do, how can you ſay ſuch (ſo long as they continue Communion with your National Church) ſeek not the Union of the Body as ſar as is fit or needful.</p>
            <p>If you ſay but neither of theſe are the caſes of thoſe you ſpeak of, becauſe they hold Communion with you to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
            <p>Very true; and you deny not, that in caſe they could not Communicate with you without ſin, but that they may lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeparate without being guilty of any breach of union.</p>
            <p>If you had here proved they might hold Communion with you without ſin, or what they extreamly ſuſpect to be ſinful, you had ſaid ſomething: but ſince you have reſerved your pretended proof thereof to the fourth Propoſition, I ſhall therefore referre my anſwer thereto.</p>
            <p>His third Propoſition.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>That the being a Member of any Church, doth oblige a man to ſubmit to all the Laws and Conſtitutions of that Church.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>I Anſwer, if by Laws and Conſtitutions he underſtands ſuch that Chriſt, either by himſelf, or his Apoſtles hath ordained, ſuch as to meet together to Pray, Praiſe, Preach, Hear, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, or Eat the Lords Supper, or to Admoniſh, Comfort, Reprove, or caſt out the Obſtinate: ſo I grant the Truth of the Propoſition.</p>
            <p>But if by Laws and Conſtitutions he means ſuch that are meerly of mens deviſing and impoſing under the penalty of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, without any command from Chriſt for ſo doing: of which kind are the Obſervations of Days, Abſtaining from Meats, Croſſing in Baptiſm, Kneeling at the Supper, Reading Prayers, and that in a Surplice; without the uſe and obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof it ſhall not be lawful for men to Preach the Goſpel, or partake of the Sacrament, but for refuſal ſhall be caſt out and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41103:19"/>not eſteemed worthy of the name of Chriſtians. In this ſence I ſay the propoſition is very falſe.</p>
            <p>And whereas he ſaith, that this Propoſition is in the general ſo unqueſtionable, that no ſober man will deny it: I on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſay, that in the general (without a ſound limitation) it is ſo miſchievous that no ſober man but may be aſhamed to aſſert it. For who will deny but that our Saviour with his Apoſtles were of the Church of the Jews and who dares ſay, that either Chriſt, or they thought themſelves obliged to obſerve the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Laws, and Traditions of that Church, either in waſhing before Meat, or in not Healing on the Sabbath-day, which Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions they made no ſcruple to tranſgreſſe, and to juſtifie ſuch Tranſgreſſion, to the ſhame and confuſion of their Impoſers. Again, who knows not that the Rulers of the Jewiſh Church had agreed, and ſo made it a Conſtitution of that Church, that if any confeſſed Chriſt he ſhould be caſt out of the Synagogue: and what Chriſtian hath the Forehead to ſay, that all the Members of that Church were obliged thereby not to confeſſe Chriſt, or to bear any part in caſting out ſuch (as did confeſſe him) from their Synagogues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He adds, this is the Baſis upon which all Societies are founded, and by which they do ſubſiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He means that the Truth of that Propoſition is at the bottom of all Societies, whether Civil or Eccleſiaſtical; but I pray how is it the Baſis of Kingdoms which are civil Societies. Thus far I grant, that all the juſt Laws Enacted by the ſupream Power in ſuch Kingdoms, do oblige all the Subjects. Anſwerably, all the Laws and Conſtitutions in the Church, that are Enacted by Jeſus Chriſt its ſupream King and Governour, do bind all the Members. But in civil Societies, if the Inferiour Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, as ſuppoſe the Heads of Corporations ſhall Enact Laws and make Conſtitutions and bind them on the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſo as in caſe of refuſal to ſubmit, they ſhall be deprived of the right and priviledges of Subjects, and that without any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from the ſupreme Power for ſo doing; I ſay in this caſe, that this Propoſition is ſo far from being the Baſis of theſe Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties, without which they cannot ſubſiſt: that I ſay, it's the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis of all Confuſion to ſuch Societies, anſwerably, if any Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41103:19"/>of Churches ſhall preſume without warrant from Chriſt, to make Laws and bind them on the Diſciples necks, upon the penalties of depriving them of the rights and priviledges of Chriſtians, as they do by excommunication, I ſay this is a meer uſurpation of the Regall power of Chriſt, and tends directly to run Churches into confuſion and all manner of diſorders as the ſad Effects thereof do cleerly demonſtrate. And whereas he ſaith, <q>To ſuppoſe a Society, and yet to ſuppoſe the members of it not under an obligation to obey its Laws and Government, is to make Ropes of ſand, and to ſuppoſe a body without ſinews and ligaments to hold the parts together.</q> I Anſwer, That tis confeſſed, that the juſt Laws of the ſupream Authority of any So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, are Sinews and Ligaments of that society; But if the Laws be either unjuſt or impoſed by any Authority inferiour to the Supream, ſuch Laws are not the natural ſinews in any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, but are certain Monſtroſities in the body politick, as ſuch kind of Sinews or Ligaments in the body naturall are reput<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which are not neceſſary or uſefull but are Impediments to a regular motion of the members, and of this kind are the Laws and Conſtitutions of Churches about which we contend.</p>
            <p>Well, but let us ſee how he clears this, he further ſaith <hi>pag.</hi> 16. <q>It muſt be acknowledged in the firſt place, that the Church muſt (as all other Societies) be entruſted with at leaſt ſo much power over her ſubjects as is neceſſary for the ſecuring of her own welfare and preſervation: For to think otherwiſe is to ſuppoſe God to have founded a Church and Intended the well being and continuance of it (which are things that every one muſt grant) and yet to ſuppoſe he hath denyed her the uſe of the means without which the well being and continuance can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be attained; which is monſtrous and contradictious.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is plain, that the Author ſpeaks here of a particular Church, as may be ſeen by a review of the propoſition, where he ſpeaks of a memberſhip with any Church, i. e. with any particular Church, and now I anſwer, Firſt,</p>
            <p>This Argument proceedeth upon an Hypotheſis, that is not neceſſarily true, as the Author imagineth, <hi>viz.</hi> that God in cauſing this or that particular Church to be planted, muſt needs Intend its continuance; for many ſuch Churches have been planted
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41103:20"/>but not continued, and certainly when it hath ſo hapned, it hath not been beſides the intention of God.</p>
            <p>Perhaps you will ſay, that was through their own fault by not making uſe of that power that God gave them to preſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſay you ſo? what then ſay you to the Church of Chriſt firſt planted at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> we read, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.1.2. that a great perſecution aroſe, and they were all ſcattered, and none left at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> except the Apoſtles. (And it is as eaſie to conceive that the Apoſtles might have been ſcattered as the reſt:) I ask now, was this Church continued? or if it was not, was it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they made not uſe of that power, that God intruſted them with for their preſervation? what would you have had them done? what, repelled force with force? I know you believe no ſuch power was intruſted with them, and yet it's certain that this diſperſion was not beſides the intention of God, therefore it is not neceſſary as you ſuppoſe, that God muſt always intend the preſervation of every particular Church he cauſeth to be plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>But in the next place let us grant your ſuppoſition, that God intends the continuance of every Church he cauſeth to be plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, what then? you ſay then, he muſt needs intruſt the ſaid Churches with ſo much power, that is neceſſary to preſerve themſelves, or elſe he is wanting to them.</p>
            <p>I deny your conſequence, becauſe ſince a Church may be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and ſo diſcontinued, as well by Armed Force from Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, as by Inteſtine Broyls ariſing from Hereſies and Schiſmes: God muſt then neceſſarily have provided every particular Church with an Army, Superior to all the power ef Perſecutors, or elſe have ingaged himſelf to work miracles for their preſervation, or elſe according to you, he muſt be thought wanting to his Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, But ſince God hath neither provided the one, nor engaged himſelf to the other, it is certain your Conſequence taken univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally cannot be true.</p>
            <p>Perhaps you will ſay if the Conſequence be not univerſally true, yet it is as to the particulars of Hereſies and Schiſmes that ariſe out of the Church: For if God had not provided the Church with ſo much power as is neceſſary to ſuppreſſe thoſe evills, he muſt be wanting in providing means for the Churches preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41103:20"/>I Anſwer, that will be ſoon ſeen, if we conſider all that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer that God hath truly given his Churches to keep them from theſe evils, which are ſo far as I underſtand, the Bible, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and the promiſe of the Spirit, to guide them that ſincerely Implore his Aid and Aſſiſtance. Now its true theſe means are ſufficient, and as much in their kind as is neceſſary, yet they are not of themſelves ſufficient, except Miniſters and People make a good uſe of them. For in caſe either the one or the other do ſinfully neglect the ſtudying of the Bible, and praying earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the guidance of the Spirit; it is very poſſible and eaſie for either of them to lapſe into Hereſies and Schiſmes, as many Churches have done, and yet when they ſo do, the have not to blame God for not intending their continuance, nor for not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording what means are in their kind ſufficient for their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. For the fault is their own in not making a due uſe and improvement of the means afforded.</p>
            <p>I know the Author is dreaming of other ſorts of means Entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Church for the preventing the deſtruction thereof by Hereſies and Schiſmes, and that is of a power of determining Controverſies in points of doctrine, and of making Laws and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances for the ſuppreſſing Schiſmes, ſo at leaſt as to oblige the members to acquieſce, which are different from ſtudying the Bible, praying for the Spirit, and to add a Living up to what they know.</p>
            <p>But by his leave, I will be bold to tell him, that ſuch a power of determining controverſies, is not a ſure means of it ſelf to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Hereſies, for what if the Paſtors themſelves, by a neglect of thoſe means I named, ſhould lapſe into Hereſies, it is certain if they came to determine, they would Eſtabliſh Hereſies, and not root them up. Nor is that power of making Laws and Canons to oblige all members to acquieſce in any ſure means to prevent or to put an end to Schiſmes, for except the members of the Church, are aſſured that what their Paſtors determine in doctrine, and what they would be Cannon oblige them to, in matters of worſhip, be agreeable to the word of God, they may juſtly make no ſcruple to diſſent in the one and the other. True indeed, if Governours of Churches could make out ſuch a power they pretend to, that they have received it from God, and that they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41103:21"/>are infallibly guided, as the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Quakers</hi> pretend in all their determinations, then ſomewhat indeed were ſpoken to the purpoſe, and the People would ſee ſome ground to take them for Oracles, and to ſtoop to their determinations, but till then it is beſt for Governours of Churches to leave the People to their Bibles, and to preſſe nothing upon them as neceſſary, but what they find to be Evidently there written and commanded.</p>
            <p>But no more of this as yet, for I have herein almoſt prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my ſelf in what I have to ſay as to that which follows.</p>
            <p>He proceeds thus, <q>That ſince the preſervation of a Church cannot be ſecured, but by a providing for a due and orderly performance of the worſhip of God, and by maintaining peace and unity among its members, it neceſſarily follows in Generall, that whatever power over her ſubjects is neceſſary in order to either of theſe things, all that at leaſt muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be Lodged in the Church, that is to ſay, in thoſe that have the Government of it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, If you mean hereby that Jeſus Chriſt hath by dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and precepts provided what is neceſſary for the due and orderly performance of Gods worſhip, and likewiſe for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving his Churches in peace and Unity, and that he hath in a ſpecial manner intruſted thoſe directions and precepts with the Paſtors of Churches, to teach and command the Churches to worſhip God according to theſe directions, and to keep unity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, and likewiſe to reprove and cenſure the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, according to the ſaid directions and precepts; ſo I yield the whole of what is ſaid. But if you mean thereby that Chriſt hath intruſted the Governours of Churches with an Arbitrary power, to inſtitute ſuch things for a pretended due and orderly worſhip, which neither were in uſe with Chriſt and his Apoſtles or thoſe firſt Churches, or that are no ways neceſſary in themſelves, but are at leaſt ſeemingly contrary to the Genius of a Goſpell-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which is Eminently ſpirituall, and to preſſe theſe under the penalties of Excommunication, as if the Churches could not duely and orderly worſhip God, and be kept in unity without them. In this ſence I deny that any ſuch power is to be ſuppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be Lodged in the Governours of the Church, for it is a power altogether uſeleſſe and impertinent, and in the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41103:21"/>deſtructive: For Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and thoſe firſt Churches worſhipped God, and kept unity in a more excellent manner than we do, and yet without the uſe of theſe humanely invented things that you Impoſe.</p>
            <p>He goes on, <q>From hence (ſaith he) it is plain that the Church hath a power to reſtrain the exerciſe of her Subjects Liberty, as to oblige them to all ſuch Laws, Rules, Orders, Ceremonies, as ſhe ſhall Eſtabliſh for the ends aforeſaid.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, When you have either better proved the neceſſity or real uſefullneſs of the laws, rules, ceremonies to the ends afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or that Chriſt hath given any ſuch power to the ſaid Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours which hitherto you have but meerly beg'd, then I will yeild to what you ſay as true, But otherwiſe it is but a poor naked Lanck Aſſertion that ſtands by it ſelf unproved, and ſo I leave it.</p>
            <p>But as to what he adds, <q>And if it be Queſtioned whether her Appointments do indeed conduce to that end; of that ſhe her ſelf is to be Judge, her members being no farther concerned therein than onely before they obey her Impoſitions to ſee that they be not repugnant to the known Laws of God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, Firſt let it be conſidered, that he grants a Judgment of diſcretion to the people, antecedent to, and a ground of their Obedience to ſuch Laws, upon this I ſay it will follow, that if the members upon ſearching the Scriptures, and praying to God for his Spirit to direct them, are left after ſuch a ſearch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſtrong perſwaſions that the very making ſuch Laws, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing ſuch Ceremonies, and binding them on the diſciples necks, under the penalties of Excommunication, is a meer uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, and that thoſe Ceremonies themſelves are of ſuch a low, carnall, beggerly conſideration, extreamly ill ſuited to the manly State of the Church, and the Spirituality of a Goſpel worſhip. I ſay if upon theſe and other conſiderations they continue ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded, that both the one, and the other, are thus repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Will and Law of Chriſt, it will be the members duty in ſuch a caſe to diſobey. It will not here be ſufficient for you to ſay, but they are miſtaken, there is no ſuch real repugnancy as they Imagine: For ſince you leave them to be Judges, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there is or is not, it is but equall that thoſe you leave to be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41103:22"/>Judges, that they ſhould be left to act according to their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in ſuch a caſe as this is, which you yield to fall under their cogniſance. And the truth is, if you will not yield ſuch a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of judgment as this is, you muſt bid them put out their eyes, and follow their Leaders in a blind Obedience, and in caſe their Leaders be blind alſo you would there in direct them to an excellent expedient how they may come all to fall into the Ditch.</p>
            <p>He Infers again, <q>Hence it will follow that the Church muſt be furniſhed with a power, to end and determine controverſies of Religion, that ariſe among its membmers, that is to ſay, to give an Authoritative deciſion of them as that all parties are bound to acquieſce in it, elſe ſhe could not preſerve her ſelf in peace and unity.</q>
            </p>
            <p>What you ſay here, may be differently underſtood, according to the nature of the points about which the controverſie is, if the matters of difference or controverſie be ſuch as may be held by both ſides, without any conſiderable damage to either of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, then I grant (that if Church Governours determine as the Apoſtle you confeſſe <hi>pag.</hi> 1. doth) that thoſe differing parties ſhould remember each other as brethren, and Communicate with each other as ſuch, forbearing to cenſure each other, as being the Lords ſervants to whom they muſt ſtand or fall, that the members ought to acquieſce in this their determination.</p>
            <p>But in caſe that Church Governours ſhall ſide with one party, and with them ſhall (contrary to the ſaid rule and practice of the Apoſtle) endeavour to force by their determination, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther party to do and ſay as they do, or elſe to excommunicate them; I ſay in this caſe, theſe Governours uſurp an Authority to themſelves above and beyond what the Apoſtle had, or thought fit to exerciſe. And Likewiſe that it is not the Duty of the party ſo Impoſed upon, to ſubmit contrary to what they conceive to be the Will of God in that caſe. For he that doth or ſaith any thing againſt his doubting Conſcience, is in the ſame Condition of Damnation, as he that doubteth and eateth, which the Apoſtle Inſtanceth in. If the points of Controverſie be about ſuch matters where thoſe that hold on one ſide do Eſpouſe ſuch doctrines or ways of worſhip that are of very dangerous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41103:22"/>to the Salvation to their Souls, (ſuch are they that are eſpouſed by <hi>Arians, Socinians, Papiſts</hi>) I ſay In theſe inſtances, if Church Governours determine on the right ſide, according to the plain Revelations of Gods word in Scriptures; the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are bound to acquieſce therein, but not meerely becauſe of their determination, but becauſe their determinations are ſounded on the Revelations of God, but in caſe the ſaid Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours ſhould, contrary to the ſaid Revelations, determine on the wrong ſide, that is to ſay, for the <hi>Socinians, Arrians, Papiſts,</hi> I ſay then, the Members were not obliged to acquieſce in theſe determinations, notwithſtanding all the pretences of Unity and Peace that may be obtained thereby.</p>
            <p>The Author being ſenſible that what he laſt ſaid, if taken in the utmoſt extent of its ſignification, would be dangerous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to limit his ſence thereof; and indeed it is but high time he ſhould.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it may be taken notice, that this Power of ending Controverſies, which we aſcribe to the Church; doth not imply any Authority over our Judgements, or that in virtue thereof ſhe can oblige us to give an inward aſſent to her determinations, any further than ſhe gives us evidence for the Truth of them; which is that extravagant Power the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>doth chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge to her ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>So far we are agreed; he adds, but our practices that ſhe can o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige us to ſubmit ſo far to her definitions, as not to act any thing contrary to them: this is abſolutely neceſſary to prevent the over run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Hereſies, and the embroyling the Church in infinite quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels and Controverſies to the deſtruction of the publick Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, firſt by conceſſion I grant according to this, here is good Proviſion made for the Purity and Peace of the Church ſo long as the Governours determine on the right ſide; But in caſe they determine on the wrong, it is then ſo bad an expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to prevent Hereſies that I do not know a more effectuall tool, for the overſpreading the Church with them than this is, for in caſe they determine for <hi>Socinians, Arrians, Popery,</hi> you ſay that the Members are obliged as to their practice though not as to their Judgements to Acquieſce in the ſaid determinations. I confeſſe herein you have ſhewed a great care of preſerving a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41103:23"/>Peace, but what a Peace is it? not a Peace of the Church of Chriſt, but the Peace of a confederacy or conſpiracy againſt the true Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But if this were true, then in the times of the predominancy of <hi>Arianiſme,</hi> when ſome hundreds of <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops met in Councel and determined wickedly againſt the Deity of Chriſt, in that point to himſelf, and never to have declared againſt that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination, for fear of diſturbing the Peace of the Church; and as for <hi>Wickliffe, Huſſe, Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> and afterwards <hi>Luther,</hi> they were all Peace breakers, in declaring againſt the abominable opinions and Antichriſtian Faith of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> they ought all of them to have kept their Judgements to themſelves, and ſo to have acquieſced in the determinations of that wicked Church: Or when <hi>Jeroboam</hi> Apoſtatized and ſet up two Calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> and commanded the people there to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; they ought onely to have kept their judgements to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but other wiſe to have conformed in outward practice to the inſtituted Worſhip, which to ſay, is contrary to the Judgement of God in that caſe who commended his 7000 in <hi>Iſrael</hi> that bowed not the knee to <hi>Baal,</hi> the commendation was, that they neither conformed in Judgement nor practice.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, that the Authour only meant that ſuch determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations only obliged the practice, Negatively; that is to ſay, that the Members are thereby bound not to practiſe any thing contrary to them.</p>
            <p>Very good let that be his meaning, now I would fain know what are thoſe acts wherein Members may be ſaid to practiſe contrary to ſuch determinations? what if they withdraw and refuſe Communion with ſuch a Church that holds to ſuch determinations; is this to be reputed a practiſing any thing to the contrary? if it be, then ſo did thoſe 7000 Iſraelites and yet are commended for ſo doing: if ſo to withdraw may not be thought to be an acting contrary, inaſmuch as the Peace may be kept notwithſtanding ſuch a withdrawing, then do you ill (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your own principles) to compell under penalties, all diſſenters to conform to you, ſince the Peace may be preſerved notwithſtanding their Non-conformity and withdrawing.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:41103:23"/>
            <p>But yet again, may a publick declaration by word of Mouth or writing, be judged an acting contrary to ſuch determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? I doubt not but you think it ſo to be.</p>
            <p>Then I demand, when the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> met together at the tryal by Sacrifice, whether God or <hi>Baal</hi> was the true God, ſays <hi>Eliſha</hi> to them, why halt you betwixt <hi>Jehova</hi> and <hi>Baal?</hi> if God be God, follow him; if <hi>Baal,</hi> follow him. Here the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were left to their choice, to conclude upon the Worſhipping of which God they were convinced to be the true God, by that tryal. In concluſion, the People being throughly convinced by a miracle that <hi>Jehova</hi> (and not <hi>Baal</hi>) was the true God: They pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly by word of mouth declared <hi>Jehovah</hi> he is God, <hi>Jehovah</hi> he is God. I ask, was this declaration an acting contrary to the eſtabliſhed Worſhip of the Land? if it was, then according to you, it was unlawful and contrary to the Peace of that corrupt Church, for they ought to have ſtood mute, and kept their Judgements to themſelves for fear of diſturbing the Peace of <hi>Baals</hi> Worſhipers.</p>
            <p>Perhaps you will ſay this was an extraordinary caſe, for a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle was here wrought by a great Prophet, which gave a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual warrant to the People for ſuch a declaration, though contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Peace of the Church. I anſwer, the immediate reaſon of this acclamation was the conviction of their judgements that <hi>Jehovah</hi> was the onely true God; the remote cauſe was the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle wrought by the Prophet, which was the cauſe of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, ſo that the immediate warrant for that acclamation, was their conviction; the remote warrant for it was the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle: now I ask you if there be the ſame degree, or a ſufficient degree of conviction in any other people, that this or that deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Governours of Churches be clearly againſt the mind of God, though the reaſon of the conviction be not a miracle wrought in their preſence, but a conſideration of what is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently declared in the Bible, that in its time had the confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of many miracles wrought by a greater than <hi>Eliſha,</hi> even by the Son of God; whether this conviction ſo wrought gives not as good and ample Authority to either Miniſters or People, to declare by Word of Mouth or Writing againſt ſuch deciſions of Church Governours, which have determined evidently againſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41103:24"/>plain Revelations, as this People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had for this their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick declaration? which if granted, then I ſay, there is no ſuch obligation that lies upon Church Members to acquieſce in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous deciſions of Church Governours, ſo as not to act or practiſe contrary there to, which you have affirmed, and I have denyed, and let the Reader judge which hath the better reaſon of his ſide for what either of us ſay, and thus have I anſwered to the third Propoſition.</p>
            <p>His Fourth Propoſition.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>That we can have no juſt cauſe of withdrawing our Communion from the Church, whereof we are Members, but when we cannot Communicate with it, without the Commiſſion of ſin.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>In this Propoſition he ſpeaks of Chriſtians as ſuppoſed to be in actual Fellowſhip with ſome viſible Church; by Church he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands either ſome particular Worſhiping Congregation, or a National Church, as for this latter notion of a Church when he hath ſhewed us, that it was, or is the will of Chriſt, that all the Chriſtians in every Nation ſhould after the manner of the Jews, be united under the ſame viſible Head of High Prieſt, and that the great body of the Nation ſhould meet by his command, at one place, as the Jews at the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for publick Worſhip, then I confeſſe he will have ſome colour for aſſerting of National Chriſtian Churches, and of a National Memberſhip therein, but till then I ſhall take the boldneſs to deny that any Chriſtian is capable of any ſuch National Church Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p>But if he doth here mean by Church a particular Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Congregation, ſuch are the parochial Churches of <hi>England,</hi> and ſuch are the Congregations of Non-conformiſts, then we ſhall conſider what he further ſaith, which is this, <hi>That no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians can have juſt cauſe of withdrawing Communion from the Church whereof they are Members,</hi> if we ſhould underſtand it indifferently of Non-conformiſts Churches as parochial, the meaning would be, that no Member that either is joyn'd to the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41103:24"/>one or the other, have juſt cauſe to withdraw Communion from either of them, but when &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If you ſay that the parochial Churches are the true regular Churches, becauſe eſtabliſhed by the Law of the Land; and all other are Schiſmaticall: I anſwer, this is ſooner ſaid than prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for did the regularity or Schiſmaticalneſſe of a Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on ſuch an externall fickle conſideration as the Law of the Land, then might one and the ſame Church be Regular or Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical as often as the wind of the <hi>Legiſlative</hi> power might chance to Change; ſo that an Act of Parliament, that makes the Epiſcopal Churches regular to day, the very ſame Churches by a change of an Act might be made Schiſmatical to morrow; and ſo if the <hi>Legiſlative</hi> Power pleaſed, both Epiſcopal, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, Presbyterian, Anabaptiſtical Churches may be regular and Schiſmatical in their turns.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, when you ſay no Communion may juſtly be with drawn from, but when it cannot be continued without the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſin, here again, I deſire to know whether by ſin you mean ſuch that may be evidenced to be ſuch, to the conviction of the impoſers; or only ſuch that is evidenced to the conviction of the Conſciences of thoſe that withdraw? you cannot in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſon require the firſt, except you will run y our ſelves upon theſe ſtraits, either to turn Papiſts, or undertake to convince the Papiſts, that the reaſon why you came off from them and their Worſhip, was becauſe you could not Communicate with them therein without ſin, we know you tell them ſo, and give yours reaſons why you ſay ſo, but notwithſtanding all you ſay they are not convinced, but yet perſiſt to call you Schiſmaticks. But what then? are you moved with their cenſure? no, for if your reaſons will not convince them: yet they ſatisfie your own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and therein you reſt, and ſo you may very reaſonably do.</p>
            <p>I deſire now but the like equity for the Non-conformiſts, and that is, that if they have reaſons ſufficient to convince their own Conſciences, that the things impoſed are ſinful though their reaſons convince not their impoſers, that you would give them that liberty of Acquieſcing therein, as you take in bearing up your ſelves againſt the Cenſures of the Papiſts.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:41103:25"/>
            <p>But yet further, What though the things Impoſed be not clearly evidenced to their own Conſciences, but onely ſo far as to leave them under ſtrong ſuſpitions that they are ſinfull? it is ſufficient to juſtifie their withdrawing; for what if the things Impoſed on the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> were ſuch as they might as law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully do or practiſe, as the Chriſtian Jews might have eaten of the once-forbidden meats? yet ſo long as their doubts remain, if they ſhould ſo practiſe they would ſin, as the Jews would have done if they had eaten ſo long as their ſcruple remained: And ſo that unqueſtionable Caſuiſt, the Apoſtle, determines in the caſe <hi>Rom.</hi> 14, 14. <hi>For I know, and am perſwaded by the Lord Jeſus, that there is nothing unclean in it ſelf, yet to him who thinks any thing unclean, to him it is unclean.</hi> So again, <hi>He that doubteth and eateth is Damned.</hi> And if it were not to light up Candles while the Sun ſhines, I would tell you, that a meer ſuſpition of a ſin, is a ſufficient ground for withdrawing Communion, in the Judgments of other very great men.</p>
            <p>So ſays that univerſally admired man, Mr. <hi>Hales,</hi> of Schiſme, <hi>pag.</hi> 8. ſays he, <q>In theſe Schiſmes which concern Fact, nothing can be a juſt cauſe of refuſing Communion, but onely to require the execution of ſome unlawful or ſuſpected Act. For not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Reaſon, but in Religion too, that maxime admits of no releaſe. <hi>Cautiſſimi cujuſque preceptum quod dubitas nefeceris,</hi> To load, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> our publick Formes with private phantaſies, (upon which we differ) is the moſt Soveraign way to perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Schiſme unto the Worlds end. Prayer, Confeſſion, Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, Reading the Scriptures, in the plaineſt and ſimpleſt manner, were matter enough to furniſh out a ſufficient Liturgy, though nothing either of private opinion, or of Church Pomp, of Garments or preſcribed Geſtures, of Imagery, of Muſick, or of many other Superfluities which creep into the Church under the name of Order and Decency, did interpoſe it ſelf. To charge Churches and Liturgies with things unneceſſary, was the firſt beginning of all Superſtition; and when ſcruple of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience began to be made, or pretended, there Schiſme began to break in he goes on, If the ſpiritual Guides of the Church would be a little ſpareing of incumbering Churches with ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities, &amp;c. there would be far leſſe Cauſe of Schiſme or Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41103:25"/>and all the inconveniences were likely to enſue, would be but this, they ſhould in ſo doing yeild a little to the imbecillity of their Inferiours, a thing which St. <hi>Paul</hi> would never have refuſed to do, Mean while I pray mark this, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever falſe or ſuſpected opinions, are made a piece of Church Liturgie, he that ſeparates is not the Schiſmatick, for it is alike unlawfull, to make a profeſſion of known or ſuſpected falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, as to put in practice unlawful or ſuſpected actions,</q>
            </p>
            <p>And of this mind is Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet,</hi> a Perſon no whit inferior to the other, whoſe words are theſe, in his <hi>Iren. p.</hi> 117. </p>
            <q>
               <p>Where any Church retaining purity of Doctrine, doth require the owning of, and conforming to, any unlawful or ſuſpected practice, men may lawfully deny Conformity to, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with that Church in ſuch things, without incurring the guilt of Schiſme; which becauſe I know it may meet with ſome oppoſition, from thoſe men who will ſooner call men Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks than prove them ſo; I ſhall offer this reaſon for it to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration; if our ſeparation from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was therefore lawfull becauſe ſhe required unlawfull things as conditions of her Communion, then wherever ſuch things are required of any Church, Non-communion with that Church in thoſe things, will be lawfull too: and where non-commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is Lawfull, there can be no Schiſme in it.</p>
               <p>If it be ſaid here, that the <hi>Popes</hi> power was a uſurpation, which is not in Lawfull Governours of Churches, it is ſoon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, that the <hi>Popes</hi> uſurpation, mainly lies in impoſing things upon mens Conſciences as neceſſary, which are doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or unlawfull: And wherever the ſame thing is done, there is an Uſurpation of the ſame nature, though not in ſo high a degree; and it may be as Lawfull to withdraw Communion from one, as well as the other. If it be ſaid, that men are bound to be ruled by their Governours, in determining what things are Lawfull, and what not: To this it is Anſwered, firſt, No true Proteſtant can ſwear blind obedience to Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours in all things: It is the higheſt uſurpation, to rob men of the Liberty of their Judgments. That which we plead for againſt the Papiſts, is, that all men have their eyes in their heads as well as the <hi>Pope,</hi> that every one hath a <hi>Judicium pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatae
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41103:26"/>diſcretionis,</hi> which is the rule of practice as to himſelf, and though we freely allow a Miniſterial power under Chriſt, in the Governours of the Church, yet that extends not to an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation upon men to go againſt the dictates of their own rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Conſcience, &amp;c. A man hath not the power over his own underſtanding, much leſſe can others have it. <hi>Nullus cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit aliquid eſſe verum quia vult credere id eſſe verum, non eſt in poteſtate hominis facere aliquid apparere intellectui ſuo verum quando volucrit.</hi> Either therefore men are bound to obey Church Governours in all things, Abſolutely, without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction or Limitation, (which if it be not uſurpation and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over others Faith in them, and the worſt of implicit Faith in others, it is hard to define what either of them is) or elſe if they be bound to obey onely in Lawfull things, I then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, who muſt be Judge what things are Lawfull, and what not? if the Governours ſtill, then the power will be Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute again, for to be ſure whatever they command, they will ſay is lawfull, either in its ſelf or as they Command it. If e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very private perſon muſt judge what is Lawfull, and what not, which is Commanded, (as when all is ſaid, every man will be his own Judge in this caſe, in things concerning his own wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare) then he is no further bound to obey, than he Judges the thing to be Lawfull which is Commanded. The plea of an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Conſcience takes not off the obligation to follow the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of it, for as he is bound to lay it down, ſuppoſing it Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, ſo he is bound not to go againſt it, while it is not laid down.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe teſtimonies are ſo clear, and backt with ſuch unanſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able reaſon, that I ſhall now not ſcruple to qualifie the propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on under conſideration thus, that where the commiſſion of ſin, (ſo ſaith he, I add or the doing any thing that is ſuſpected to be ſinfull,) is required as the condition of Communion, there a withdrawing is Lawfull and not at all Schiſmatical.</p>
            <p>Having thus given an account of theſe different ſcenes, in which both he and I do underſtand the ſeveral parts of this propoſition, I ſhall now come to examine what he hath ſaid for the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof,</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:41103:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>There are</hi> (ſaith he, p. 19.) <hi>but two caſes wherein it can be Lawfull to withdraw Communion from a Church; one is, when the Church requires of us, as a Condition of her Communion, an acknowledgment and profeſſion of that to be truth, which we know to be an errour; the other is, when ſhe requires of us the joyning with her in ſome Practice which we know to be againſt the Laws of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though I will not be ſo confident to ſay with this Author that only in theſe two caſes it may be Lawfull to withdraw Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, for there may be a third and a fourth, which neither he nor I may at preſent think of. Yet ſo far I agree with him, that theſe two caſes mentioned are juſt cauſes of withdrawing Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. But whereas he ſaith, that the errour muſt be known to be ſuch, and the practice known to be againſt the Law of God, to that I ſay, that knowledge implyes certainty. But I ſay if the errours and practices be but ſuſpected, ſo as the Conſcience doth but doubt, it is ſufficient: as I have proved from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, and the teſtimonies and reaſons of Mr. <hi>Hales,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingſleet.</hi> This being premiſed, I ſhall now proceed to a Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of thoſe grounds which he ſuppoſeth Non-conformiſts plead as ſufficient cauſes of their ſeparation, as they are Enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated and Affirmed by him to be inſufficient.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he ſaith, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſcriptural impoſitions can be no ſufficient cauſe to warrant a Separation from a Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwer, By unſcriptural impoſitions (he ſuppoſeth as he tells us) is meant, <hi>no more than what is neither commanded nor forbid in Scriptures, neither by Particular or General Rules.</hi> Thus when he hath by a falſe ſuppoſition faſhioned and erected a man of Straw, he then puſhes him quite down with the horns of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemma, and Fancyes to himſelf a great victory, for from that ſuppoſition he thus argues, <hi>Thoſe unſcriptural impoſitions which are neither commanded nor forbid, by any general or particular rules in Scripture, are eitherin themſelves Lawfull or unlawfull, if unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, then they are againſt ſome Particular or Generall ſcriptural rule, &amp; ſo cannot fall under the notion of unſcriptural Impoſitions, which are ſuppoſed to be againſt neither of theſe Rules, if lawfull, then it canot be imagined how their being commanded, can make them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, ſo that in this caſe there is no ſin in yeilding obedience, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41103:27"/>conſequently no juſt cauſe of withdrawing our Communion.</hi> This is the ſtrength of what he hath ſaid to this firſt caſe.</p>
            <p>My Anſwer is this, I wonder which of his diſſenters gave him ground to ſuppoſe that ever any of them took unſcriptural Impoſitions, for ſuch things that were neither Commanded nor Forbid, by any General or Special Rule in Scripture; if thus you care not upon what Sandy premiſes you build your Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, who can help it?</p>
            <p>But I pray be pleaſed to let me tell you what we our ſelves mean, by unſcriptural Impoſitions.</p>
            <p>They are ſuch things, the religious uſe whereof is impoſed upon Chriſtians, in the Worſhip and Service of God, under the penalties of depriving Miniſters of their office, or the exerciſe thereof, and of depriving both them and private Chriſtians of the liberty of enjoying Goſpell Ordinances or the Priviledges of a Viſible Church ſtate, by the cenſure of excommunication, which are things that are not either Commanded, or directly For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden in Scripture, in any expreſſe terms; for we confeſſe that there is not the word Surplice, or ſign of the Croſs, &amp;c. ſo much as named in Scripture, and upon this account, we allow them the name of unſcriptural. But we ſay moreover, that the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious uſe of theſe things in the Worſhip of God, and much more the impoſitions of them as neceſſary Conditions of Communion, are againſt General Rules, and Inſtances in the like kind diſ-al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in Scripture, from whence we by deduction gather the unlawfulneſſe, and ſinfulneſſe thereof, and upon this latter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, I call them antiſcriptural, as being religious Cuſtomes and Uſages contrary to theſe General rules, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus having given you our true ſence and meaning, of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptural Ceremonies, now I anſwer to your dilemma.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Either</hi> you ſay, <hi>theſe things thus impoſed are in themſelves law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or unlawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, Your argument as you form it, is trivial and not to the purpoſe; for it ſpeaks not to the Queſtion under Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, for the Queſtion is not about the nature of the things im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, taken Abſolutely; but about the Religious uſe of thoſe things in the worſhip and ſervice of God. Thus then your argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ought to proceed: Either the religious uſe of theſe things
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41103:27"/>impoſed in the Worſhip and Service of God, is lawfull or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull.</p>
            <p>I anſwer Now directly, the Religious uſe of them is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and this antecedently to the impoſing of them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the impoſing of them cannot make them lawfull.</p>
            <p>Here had been a fit place for you to have ſhewn your ſtrength, (if you had any) in Convincing us, that the Religious uſe of theſe things in Gods Worſhip, is Lawfull antecedently to the Impoſition. But we have not a word hereof, and therefore ſince I find no more oppoſition therein, I might juſtly diſmiſs this firſt thing without any further Reply.</p>
            <p>Yet if any ſhall ask for what reaſon is it, that we ſay that ſuch a uſe of them is unlawfull? I anſwer, our reaſons are ready, and they are ſuch that do at leaſt Convince our Conſciences ſo far as to doubt and really ſuſpect their uſe to be unlawful; Which is ſufficient to make their impoſition a warrantable ground of withdrawing (though the Evidence thereof be not ſo great, as to Convince our Gainſayers; no nor poſſibly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate fully the unlawfulneſs thereof to our own Conſciences) as hath been already proved. If I be yet urged to ſhew our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of this our perſwaſion or ſuppoſition; Methinks it were reaſon enough if I onely told ſuch, that theſe things impoſed, are only the productions of a humane ſpirit, and are beholding for their Continuance in being, to the Traditions of men; and ſo hold in no reſpect of Chriſt the head, which is ſufficient, not only in my opinion, but in the judgment of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> to give members of Churches Caution againſt the reception of them, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Beware leſt any man make a prey of you through Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, and vain deceit, after the Traditions of men, after the Rudiments of the World, and not after Chriſt.</hi> Whoever plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to ſee an excellent paraphraſe upon this verſe, let him read it in Mr. <hi>John Dale</hi> in his expoſition on this Epiſtle, which hath the Imprimatur <hi>Tho. Tomkins Ex</hi> Aed. <hi>Lambeth,</hi> and therefore I hope the teſtimony of this excellent perſon may obtain ſome repute; his words are theſe, </p>
            <q>
               <p>The Scriptures calls thoſe doctrines, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men, which have men only for their Authors; which come from men, and not form God, theſe with the errours of Philoſophy, of which the Apoſtle ſpeaks immediately before,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41103:28"/>may bear the ſame name, ſince they both flow'd from the ſpirit of men, and had no other ſource but this imagination. A little after he ſaith, Whence it doth appear, that no productions of an humane ſpirit, are receivable in Evangelicall Religion, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe that are ſuppoſed by ſome pretended reaſons, nor thoſe that are ſounded upon Uſe and Antiquity; they are all of them nothing but ſolly and vanity in the ſight of God, with what Colour ſoever they be painted over; And though men boaſt of their utility, they are extreamly hurtfull, as peſtering Conſciences, and buſying them about things which God hath not ordained, and turning them aſide from his pure ſervice to matters of nought.</p>
               <p>Accordingly you ſee that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt rejects, and roughly thruſts away all the Traditions of the Phariſees, how much eſteemed ſoever they were for their Antiquity and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Uſe: reproaching them that by holding faſt thoſe Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Men, they did let looſe the Commandements of God. Applying to them thoſe words of the Lord in <hi>Iſaiah, In vain do they Honour me, teaching for doctrines the Traditions of men.</hi> As indeed it's an unſufferable preſumption, that men ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to preſcribe the form of Gods ſervice, eſpecially after the declaration which himſelf hath vouchſafed to make of his holy will, nor is there one among men that would indure his ſervant ſhould treat him in that manner, and inſtead of obeying his Orders, and cauſing others to diſpatch them; fall a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophiſing in his houſe, and giving his Family a new Rule to obſerve, as if he were wiſer than his Maſter. I know well the Authors of theſe Traditions, and thoſe that follow them, are not without fine reaſons, to palliate their temerity; but it is Evident that they do the very ſame for Subſtance, Neither is it to be doubted, but a Servant that ſhould be culpable of ſuch a vanity, would alledge likewiſe his motive and deſignes, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that would give them audience. But Common ſenſe dictat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the meaneſt capacities, that ſuch undertaking Spirits, merit not ſo much as to be heard, eſpecially where God is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, in Compariſon of whom, they with all their ſufficiency are but poor worms of the Earth. Hold we firm therefore this Foundation of the Apoſtle, that the Traditions of men ought
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41103:28"/>to have no place in Religion, it concerns me not to inform my ſelf of their age whether they be the Traditions of Men An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient or Modern, it ſufficeth that I know they are Traditions of men, having the Apoſtles advertiſement we ſhould not be moved with any reaſon, or ſplendor, or antiquity they may come cloathed with; if you would have me receive them, ſhew me that they are preſcriptions of Gods, inſtitutions of his Chriſt, Doctrines of his Scriptures; without this, However ſpecious you make them appear to me, I ſhall never believe it; it is but to make a prey of me, and your diligence ſhall have no effect but the making me ſuſpect them ſo much the more.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Thus far you have had the Judgement of as great Divines as the Church in this laſt age hath produced, and who ever thinks there is not reaſon enough in this diſcourſe to give Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation ſufficient to tender Conſciences, at leaſt to ſuſpect, if not to be confident of the unlawfulneſs, of the Religious uſe of theſe things in the ſervice of God: I know not what ſuch will yeild to be ſufficient, nor would I wiſh ſuch any greater puniſhment for their being otherwiſe minded, than that they were obliged to give a more rational account of this verſe of the Apoſtle; and likewiſe to enervate the force of this Authors reaſon here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</p>
            <p>In confeſſe ſuch is the vanity of mans mind, that whilſt he either not at all, or very negligently hath regard to that Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie that God hath over his Worſhip; (as is frequently taken notice of in Scriptures) is apt to think of theſe fictitious Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Worſhip as very indifferent and harmleſs matters; for who could of a ſudden think there is any good ground of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſuch a buſineſſe about a Surplice, and the ſign of a Croſſe in Baptiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as is made among us? nor is it matter of much wonder to me, to ſee ſome well meaning Men, yea, and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things Wiſe and Learned, when they hear of the plauſible pretexts for their inſtitution, to be perſwaded into a conceit of their uſefulneſs: and why not? when I find <hi>Nathan</hi> in a like caſe highly deceived, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.8. When <hi>David</hi> acquainted him with his purpoſe to build a houſe for God, ſaith <hi>Nathan</hi> go, and do all that is in thy Heart, for the Lord is with thee: here was a well meant propoſal, and a very ſudden and raſh anſwer,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41103:29"/>as appears by that ſudden check that the Lord that very night put to it, <hi>v.</hi> 4. and it came to paſſe that night that the Word of the Lord came to <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, ſaying, go and tell my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>David,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Shalt thou build me an Houſe for me to dwell in?</hi> again, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>Speak I a word with any of the Tribes of Iſrael, whom I commanded to feed my People Iſrael, ſaying why build ye not me an houſe of Cedar?</hi> it is evident from hence that though both <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Nathans</hi> meaning were good, yet the work deſigned by the one, and approved by the other; had it been ſet upon and finiſhed, had been evil, becauſe there was no word of the Lord to warrant it, which is implyed in the anſwer, God makes. That we are not ſingular in giving this Interpretation, ſee <hi>Pools Synopſis Critic.</hi> on the place, thus, <hi>vade, fac. hoc dicit ſenſu humano erravit Nathan, quia Deum non conſuluit, mirum eſt sum ita temerè pronunciare, quia Dominus tecum eſt</hi>] <hi>eſt Paralogiſmus a ſecundum quid and Simpliciter. Ver.</hi> 4. <hi>In illâ nocte,</hi>] <hi>Deus non patitur ſuos diù decipi cùm videat eos Simpliciter errare. v.</hi> 5. <hi>Numquid tu aedificabis?</hi>] <hi>qu. cur David retrahitur &amp; Judaei in</hi> Hag. 1. <hi>Arguuntur quod non aedificent? Reſpond. quod David non haberet verbum Domini, Judaei autem haberent. cui praecepi ut paſceret populum,</hi>] <hi>voluntas Davidis bona fuit, &amp; placuit Deo, ſed in eo erravit quod non haberet verbum Dei, a quo expèctare debuit, &amp; Locum, &amp; tempus, &amp; peculiare mandatum.</hi> The ſumme of the whole is this <hi>Davids</hi> will was good, but to have done the thing willed, had been evil; becauſe there was no command from God for doing it: the caſe here is much alike peradventure the will of thoſe that firſt invented the religious uſe of theſe things might be good, and yet the uſe of them might be bad; for the very ſame reaſon becauſe they want the word of the Lord for their warrant.</p>
            <p>Thus have I given you ſome further account, why at leaſt we ſuſpect the Religious uſe of theſe things in Gods Service to be unlawful, antecedent to any impoſition. If you will ſtill call for more of our reaſons, I tell you they are ready, and you ſhould have them, but that I fear the ſwelling of the book beyond the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary readers patience and purſe: but I wonder what you can ſay that amounts to as good reaſon for their lawfulneſs, as hath been already given againſt their lawfulneſs. As for that text ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41103:29"/>monly urged, <hi>let all things be done in decency and order,</hi> it will do you little Service in ſuch like caſes as we have inſtanced in, for the Apoſtle doth there ſpeak of ſuch a decency and order, that doth ariſe from the Nature of things, and not of ſuch that have their reſult onely from the arbitrarious Fancies of Men, of the former kind of order and decency the God of Nature is the Author, of the other mans imagination; for the undecency and diſorder there reproved, is ſuch as ſpeaking in a ſtrange Tongue to the Church met together for edification, which ſometimes none underſtood but him that ſpake, or elſe paradventure the ſpeaking of more than one at one time, which could not but breed confuſion or be unprofitable, or ſuch as conſiſted in ſome Womens forwardneſſe to teach and inſtruct the Church, which conſiſted much of men, which was contrary to that order where in God had placed that Sex in Subjection to men, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were very unmeet to be imployed as their inſtructors. But what is there in theſe Ceremonies, or in the Nature of them, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted from mans imagination, that hath any thing of this natural order and decency, for whether you think it or not: yet certainly, it's a very diſorderly thing for a Miniſter to ſpeak a Sermon of Greek or Latine, to a Church that onely under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Engliſh; or for many to be ſpeaking together, but lay aſide Imagination and I wonder what indecency is in praying without a Surplice or Adminiſtring Baptiſm without the ſign of the Croſſe?</p>
            <p>So that it's evident theſe Ceremonies fell not under that kind of order and decency of which the Apoſtle ſpeaks, and therefore there is no warrant from that text for their Inſtitution or their uſe.</p>
            <p>In Truth their pretended decency, is much like that decency that <hi>David</hi> imagined, which was the reaſon of his contriving for God a houſe, thus he reaſoned; ſhall I dwell in a houſe of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar, and is it decent or comely that the Ark of God ſhould dwell within Curtaines? one would have thought his reaſon from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency was good, but as you have heard God anſwered his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and reproved his humane Judgement therein, ſo that an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from decency in ſuch matters is very falacious: yet again, I have ſeen ſome men arguing thus, if it be not lawful to uſe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41103:30"/>things religiouſly in the ſervice of God without a warrant from the Word, why then do we Religiouſly make uſe of Churches to meet in, Pulpits to Preach in, Communion Table to eat the Lords Supper on? are not all theſe things Religiouſly uſed in the Worſhip of God, or have we an expreſſe word for them? Or why do we admit of the dividing of the Bible into Chapters, and the addition of the Contents, and dividing the Chapters into Verſes? or why do we admit of the turning <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms into Meeter, and ſinging them in ſuch Tunes that are made for them, have we any expreſſe word for theſe?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, as to the uſe of Churches, Pulpits, Tables, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe they are uſed as convenient circumſtances of the Worſhip of God, but then I ſay, their conveniency ariſes from the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Acts of worſhip, and a natural neceſſity of ſuch kind of things for the performance of theſe Acts of worſhip conveniently, and are not the reſults of mere phantaſy and imagination; for certainly it's more than a phantaſy to ſay, it's convenient that when the worſhippers meet together for worſhip, they ſhould have a capacious houſe to meet in, to ſhelter them from the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the weather, or it's more than bare fancy to ſay, its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient that the Preacher ſhould ſtand above the people, both to eaſe him of the inconveniency of the croud, and that he may be better heard, and ſo it may be ſaid of the Table, how can the Lords supper be conveniently adminiſtred without a Table to put the Bread and the VVine upon? but as for your Ceremonies, there is no neceſſity at all of them, but they are the only births of an Arbitrarious vain Imagination, for the ordinances may be well enough adminiſtred without them.</p>
            <p>Beſides I anſwer, that theſe things now named are uſed as circumſtances convenient, and in ſome ſort naturally neceſſary to the Acts of worſhip, yet I deny, that ever when they are ſo uſed, that they ought to be Religiouſly uſed; a thing is then Religiouſly uſed, not barely when I uſe it in worſhip, (for ſo I uſe my Cloak and band in worſhip which yet I uſed not Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly) but to uſe a thing in worſhip religiouſly, is when I uſe it for religious ends, as to the pleaſing of God, and the edifying of my ſelf and others in religious matters, now when we meet in a Church, or ſtand in a Pulpit, or cat the Lords Supper on the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41103:30"/>Table, we do not think that there is any thing in thoſe places that render us or our worſhip any whit the more pleaſing to God; for if we met on a Mountain, or on a Sea ſhore, and taught out of a boat, or in caſe of neceſſity by reaſon of perſecution, did eat the Lords Supper upon the graſſe, provided we did all in Spirit and Truth, our ſervices were every whit as acceptable as in, from, or on the other places; and it's a meer Idle ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious conceit to think otherwiſe: but now as for theſe Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, either you think to pleaſe God by them and edifye the Church, or you do not; if you do, then you fall under the like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof of God to <hi>David,</hi> when did god bid you do ſuch things? or when did he tell you that then he was pleaſed with them? if not, they are altogether impertinent and uſeleſſe, for as I have ſhewed they ariſe not out of the Nature of things, but meerly out of phantaſy and therefore ought to be let alone, for aſſuredly man doth not, much leſſe doth God care to be trifled with, in matters of Worſhip; as to the other things inſtanced in, as dividing the Scriptures into Chapters, and giving the Contents thereof, to that I ſay though there is not a particular expreſſe command for it, yet there is a general command to thoſe that are Miniſters of Chriſt to explain the whole Councel of God to his people, and ſuch addition now named, with the giving of the Contents of each part, any Miniſter of the Goſpel hath a warrant to do by virtue of the ſaid general command given to Miniſters; and upon this account thoſe that did divide them, did well and warrantably, for it is one of the commanded works of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to divide the Word aright.</p>
            <p>As for the digeſting the Chapters into verſes, the direct and immediate deſign thereof was onely to help the Memory, nor do thoſe that read Scriptures make any other uſe of them; I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver underſtood that any uſed thoſe figures with any conceit, as if they pleaſed God more with reading the Word with them, than they ſhould do if they read it without them, or as if they thought they were any direct helps to their Faith or devotion; and as for Singing Pſalms, there is a Word that gives Foundation to that Ordinance, as there is none for humane Ceremonies, and as for the Melody that there is made, that likewiſe hath its Foundation in the word; ſo then there is nothing done by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41103:31"/>
               <hi>Davids</hi> words into Meeter, but only a putting them into a poſture fit for to be ſung, which the Nature of that duty makes neceſſary, and therefore gives warrant thereto. But as for the Ceremonies contended for, They have no ſuch original, but as I have ſaid only depend upon mens imagination, for there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in any Act of worſhip that needs or calls for them.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſhewn you ſome of thoſe grounds we have to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the lawfulneſſe of the things impoſed, and likewiſe laid naked the weakneſs of ſome of your reaſons from which you think them lawful, before I conclude my anſwer to this firſt part of your charge againſt us; a little to try the force of your conſequence: let us therefore for once ſuppoſe that the things impoſed were ſuch that might be lawfully uſed, for Religious ends, in the worſhip of God; what then? you <hi>ſay it then follows that they do not become unlawful becauſe impoſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, firſt by conceſſion it is true, were they lawful to be done, I cannot ſay that the command would alter the nature of theſe things to make them unlawful, but yet I ſay, this will not excuſe the impoſer, nor him that obeys the impoſition, from ſin; not the impoſer, for he uſurps a power over another Lords Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, in things that do not concern him: and ſecondly, if the impoſer injoyns thoſe little and ſuppoſe lawful things under ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere penalties, ſuch as deprivation, excommunication, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the one he ſins as a uſurper of Chriſts Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, in the other as cruel; nor is he that obeys the impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, Innocent; but I do not lay his guilt upon doing the thing ſuppoſed lawful, but inaſmuch as by his obedience thereto he doth ſeem to own ſuch an uſurpation, and to acknowledge the impoſer his Maſter in ſuch matters, wherein Chriſt only is his Lord; and upon this account I ſay, he ſins, inaſmuch as he tranſgreſſeth that Command of Chriſt, <hi>Let no man be called Maſter or Father,</hi> that is let none be owned as your Maſter or Father, in theſe matters of Faith and VVorſhip, <hi>for</hi> in ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>ye have but one Maſter even Christ, Math.</hi> 23.8.10. Thus I have ſaid what I conceive is a ſufficient anſwer to your firſt charge when you ſay, that our ſeparation upon the account of unſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Ceremonies impoſed, is not ſufficient to excuſe us from Schiſme.</p>
            <p>Secondly he ſaith, <hi>That the Church requiring from us any
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41103:31"/>doubtful or ſuſpected practices, as Conditions of her Communion, is not a juſt cauſe of Separation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have proved the falſhood of this Propoſition already, from the teſtimonies of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who is a far bettter Caſuiſt than the Author, who hath declared that Chriſtians are under the Obligations of obeying the dictates of their Conſciences, or not acting contrary thereto though their Conſciences be under a miſtake. And beſides I have given you in the teſtimony of Mr. <hi>Hales,</hi> and the reaſons of Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> againſt this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Authour, which I think will be long enough before he ſolidly anſwer.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the Authour of this Propoſition doth eſſay to give a reaſon of what he here aſſerts, I ſhall not be ſo uncivil as not to take notice thereof, but will return him a fair anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That is no juſt cauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for we must at leaſt have as much certainty of the unlawfulneſſe of the Action enjoyned, as we have of our Obligation to the Authority that enjoynes them, before we withdraw our obedience to it; otherwiſe we do not proceed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſafe grounds: but now we are abſolutely certain that God hath commanded us to obey them that have the rule over us, but we are not certain that the Actions we here ſpeak of, are any where for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid by him, for if they were they would be no longer doubtful or ſuſpected, they would be certain ſins; ſo that if we will follow the ſurer ſide, as all Chriſtians in theſe caſes are bound to do, we muſt continue our obedience to the Church, notwithſtanding we ſuſpect or doubt of the lawfulneſs of her commands,</hi> Thus far he—</p>
            <p>I anſwer, this Argument (notwithſtanding the prittineſs of its contrivance is certainly falatious; for <hi>ex vero nihil ſequi poteſt niſi verum,</hi> for the rule there laid down of always obeying the Church Rulers, where the Conſcience is in doubt, is in many inſtances a ready way to involve many a weak Conſcience in damnable guilt. For ſuppoſe there had been many a doubtful Conſcience among the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Ahabs</hi> time, as it ſeems there were, who halted betwixt the VVorſhip of <hi>Jehovah</hi> and <hi>Baal;</hi> ſuppoſe yet a little further, that the Conſciences thus doubting were rather inclined to believe <hi>Jehovah</hi> the true God, and <hi>Baal</hi> but an Idol, but yet were not abſolutely certain; what ſay you
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41103:32"/>now? what Councel would you have given ſuch an one, if he had askt your advice? do but look how ill-favouredly ſuch an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer as this would ſeem; true might you ſay, according to your rule, I do believe that <hi>Jehovah</hi> is the only true God, and <hi>Baal</hi> but a Devil, and that your worſhiping a Devil is a damnable ſin; but as for you, you are not ſo certain hereof as I am, yet your Conſcience is inclined to believe as I do; my advice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is this, that ſince your Rulers have commanded you to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that Devil, I Counſel you ſo to do, till your Conſcience be better reſolved; and why? becauſe you are certain God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded you to obey your rulers, but you are not yet ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that <hi>Baal</hi> is a Devil; I dare ſay you abhor ſuch a reſolution of the caſe, and yet I ſee not but you muſt be forced to give no better, if you follow the rule laid down in this argument; I might inſtance in other like caſes, as if a Jew in the dayes of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſiahs being in the Fleſh, had been inclined to believe in him as the Meſſiah, but yet was not ſo abſolutely certain thereof, as he was of this command, thou ſhalt obey the Rulers of thy people; according to you, he muſt go againſt the inclination of his doubting, Conſcience in diſowning and rejecting Chriſt that he might yeild obedience to his Rulers, who command, him ſo to do; in like manner, if a poor man were inclined to believe the Maſſe Idolatry, he muſt go on in that ſin againſt his doubting Conſcience till he comes to be as certain it is Idolatry, as he is that God hath commanded us to obey our Rulers.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid, it is evident there is a fallacy in your Argument; and now to ſhew you where it lies, give me leave to tell you, it lies in your arguing from particulars to an Univerſal, <hi>vel a dicto ſecundum quid ad dictum ſimpliciter.</hi> That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am ſure that God hath Commanded me to obey my rulers in ſome things, therfore I am ſure that God hath Commanded me to obey my Rulers in every thing, yea, in ſuch things which I ſuſpect to be ſin: Do but you make this Evident, that in that very Command which I ſuſpect to be ſinfull, that I may be ſure that God hath Commanded me to obey, and then I will give up the Cauſe. But this you can never do, for upon thoſe very ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, upon which I ſuſpect the ſinfulneſſe of the Command, upon the ſame Arguments I ſuſpect whether God hath given
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41103:32"/>them Authority to Command, or whether God would have me to obey; for I can never be ſure, that God hath Commanded me to obey my Rulers in ſuch inſtances where I ſuſpect my Rulers Command me to ſin. So that, whereas your Argument ſuppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that a Doubting conſcience may be more certain that God hath Commanded him to obey his Rulers, than he is of the thing he doubts; and ſo he is therefore to take the ſurer ſide, and ſo to obey his Rulers againſt his Conſcience. I have made the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry appear, by ſhewing that a man can never be ſure that God hath Commanded him to obey his Rulers in ſuch caſes where he ſuſpects they Command him to ſin. So that in obeying them he doth not take the ſurer ſide. Thus is the ſtrength of this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo the ſtrength of his ſecond (Charged upon the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts) broken, wherein he hath been endeavouring to prove, they have no juſt Cauſe of Separation, though it be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of avoiding what they ſuſpect to be ſinfull which is made the Condition of Communion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſaith he, <hi>Neither can it be true that Errours in a Church, as to matter of Doctrines; or Corruptions, as to matter of Practice, (ſo long as theſe Errours and Corruptions are only ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, but not impoſed) can be a ſufficient Cauſe of Separation: The reaſon is, becauſe the things are not ſin in us, ſo long as we do not joyn with the Church in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, Firſt, I would fain know what kind of Errours of Doctrines, or Corruptions of Practice, you do here mean? for they are of divers ſorts and kinds, and accordingly what you here ſay may be either True or Falſe.</p>
            <p>If by Errours of Doctrine you mean, ſuch that are conſiſtent with the holding of Chriſt the head, or ſuch that touch not upon the Fundamentals of the Chriſtian Doctrine; ſome ſuch were thoſe in the Apoſtles days, that related to the Abſtaining from meats, and obſervation of days; in ſuch caſes doubtleſſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ought without impoſing to bear with one another, and to continue Communion with each other, notwithſtanding ſuch differences, which was the Apoſtles counſel in that caſe; in this ſence, what you ſay is true. Or if by Corruptions in Practice, you ſhould mean ſuch infirmities, that all Members of Churches are ſubject to more or leſſe, (for who can ſay, that he is without
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41103:33"/>ſin?) in this ſence you are right; or if you mean by errours and Corruptions, ſuch that are of a more Groſſe, and Hainous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which are not publickly known, or of which the Members cannot have ſufficient proof, for the conviction of themſelves, that thoſe that are accuſed are really guilty, ſo alſo I grant what is here ſaid; for till it be evident by ſome overt Act, that <hi>Judas</hi> hath a Devill, and is a Traytor; he ought to be look'd on as an Apoſtle, and might be heard.</p>
            <p>In like manner, if the Governours of the Church, were with many of the Members, <hi>Arrians</hi> or <hi>Socinians</hi> in their judgments; but not known evidently to be ſuch, it may be the Duty of ſound Chriſtians not to withdraw Communion from them.</p>
            <p>But if it ſhall ſo fall out, that the Governours of a Church, and a great body of the People be ſo erroneous, and this ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently known, and though reproved, yet they abidè obſtinate maintainers thereof; I ſay in this Caſe it is ſufficient ground for ſound Members to withdraw, and ſave themſelves from ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous a Society: and why? becauſe I may not lawfully joyn with ſuch a Church, where poſſibly I may, every time I joyn the Lord Chriſt and the Holy Ghoſt, Blaſpheme; whoſe Deity is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by theſe Sects: nor may I joyn, leſt I indanger my Faith; for evill words do not only Corrupt good manners, but have a direct tendency to corrupt a ſound Faith; and certainly the ſafety of a Soul is of greater worth, than the preſervation of a Corrupt Peace, or Unity of a Corrupt Church.</p>
            <p>And what I have ſaid upon a ſuppoſition of ſuch groſſe errours in the Rulers, and many of the people of a Church; the ſame may be ſaid of either Idolaters, or groſly profane practices; for if Miniſters, or many of the Members, ſhould degenerate to a Popiſh Idolatry; or ſhould prove Common Drunkards, or Whore-mongers, or Oppoſers, &amp;c. and being admoniſhed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſhould deride the admonition as Preciſe, and fanatical: or if the Members only were Commonly ſo, and the Rulers witting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Connive thereat, and ſeek not their Cure, by Reproofs and Cenſures, as Chriſt hath commanded in ſuch caſes; I ſay again, it is a ſufficient ground for the ſound Members to withdraw (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if a more pure Church may be had) yea though neither theſe errours or practices are impoſed; and that firſt, leſt under
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41103:33"/>the pretence of Peace, they ſhould be guilty of the greateſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſſe, and that is, the hardning and incouraging, them in their abominable Impieties. Again, becauſe the ſound ought, by the law of God and Nature, to provide for their own ſafety. Certainly if there be a Contagion in evill words to corrupt good manners, there is much more in wicked Practices; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they cannot but be in apparent danger by Communicating with ſuch, and certainly in ſo doing, there is nothing done con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Fundamental reaſon of Chriſts Inſtituting diſcipline in his Church, which as I conceive was for the Cure of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound, and for the preſervation of the ſound, from the infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the unſound: Now if no care be taken for the cure of the ſame, but that infectious Crew is kept in the Church to the palpable endangering of the ſound, it is apparent that the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of diſcipline are rooted up, and in effect there is no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline at all, and that therefore every good Chriſtian may ſeek his ſafety as he can, ſince he cannot obtain it in a Church by the means of the Goſpel Diſcipline, which through the Corruption of the Rulers, and the ſwaying part of the Corrupt Members is made void.</p>
            <p>But no more of this till by and by, when I ſhall have a freſh occaſion to ſpeak further to this point.</p>
            <p>At preſent let us again return to inquire into a full ſence of his Propoſition if by any means we can find it out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſay in generall terms, without any Limitation, that errors in Doctrine, and Corruptions in practice, when found in a Church, but not impoſed, is no juſt ground of ſeparation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, Methinks by this generall way of Expreſſing your ſelf, that you are not afraid of your Readers underſtanding this Propoſition without any Limitation.</p>
            <p>I pray tell me, what if <hi>Socinian</hi> or <hi>Popiſh</hi> Errours and Corrupt practices, were got into the Rulers of a Church, and a great bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the People, and that they ſhould only tollerate them, but not impoſe them on any, what hinders (if what you here ſay be true) but that every ſound Chriſtian may, yea and ought to Communicate with ſuch a Church? eſpecially if Providence had caſt him into ſuch a place; where no other could be had: ſo that one of a Proteſtant Faith, might lawfully joyn with a Popiſh
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41103:34"/>Church, not only in hearing their Friars Preach, but likewiſe in receiving the Maſs of them; provided they would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> him to profeſs their Errors, or to Practiſe the Super<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Idolatry in the Maſs: but permit him to receive it in both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in his own ſence, though he knows the Prieſt delivers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the reſt of the Communicants receive it in the Popiſh ſence</p>
            <p>I would not be ſo unmerciful to charge you as holding this, but this I ſay, that ſo much ſeems to follow Clearly from this your Poſition, if taken without any Limitation; and I can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern none in this Paragraph.</p>
            <p>If you ſay, that there is enough ſaid by you, <hi>pag.</hi> 22. concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Popiſh Church, to clear you in this particular: I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, It is true, you ſay there, that the great and general Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> both in Doctrine and Practice, doth endanger the Salvation of ſuch as Communicate with her; and that therefore a totall ſeparation from her, and an erection of new Churches may be Lawfull.</p>
            <p>I ſay notwithſtanding all this, yet I doubt whether you there mean, that her Errors and Corruptions in themſelves, or of their own nature do ſo far endanger mens Salvation, that though they were not impoſed, yet we were bound to a totall ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: or do you mean, they therefore ſo endanger our Salvation becauſe impoſed, as to warrant ſuch a ſeparation.</p>
            <p>If your Propoſition there, may be underſtood in the ſormer ſence; then what you ſay here (taken univerſally) muſt needs be falſe; for if the very being of ſome ſorts of Errors and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions in a Church, (though not impoſed) are ſo dangerous as to warrant a ſeparation; how can it then be univerſally true (as you ſeem here to aſſert) that Errours in Doctrine, and Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Practice, (ſo long as they are only ſuffered, but not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed) cannot be a ſufficient Cauſe of ſeparation? but if you are there to be underſtood in the latter ſence, that is to ſay, that the Errours and Corruptions of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> only as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed are ſo dangerous to mens ſalvation, as to warrant a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; then that which I even now ſuggeſted is true; that Chriſtians may Lawfully here be Baptized, go to Maſs with the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> Provided they were not forced to make a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of believing their Errors, or had leave to receive thoſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41103:34"/>with all the Superſtitions thereto belonging, in their own ſence; though it was well known, that they adminiſtred them in an other. I will not at preſent (as aforeſaid) charge this opinion upon the Author: though it ſeems to be a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence rightly inferred from this, and other principles of his in this diſcourſe, becauſe he ſaith <hi>pag.</hi> 31. <hi>A man may believe a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and not believe all that follows from it;</hi> So that at no hand are we to charge ſuch Conſequences upon him, unleſs he doth explicitly own them, but whether you will explicitly own them or no, I am not certain: Yet this I know, that I have heard a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> not ſcruple to profeſſe that he would, for Peace ſake, uſe all the Popiſh Ceremonies of Cream and Spittle in Baptiſme, as well as the ſign of the Croſs, provided his Rulers did impoſe them, but ſo as that he was left to his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, is not to uſe them to the Popiſh Superſtitious ends: But why ſuch an one may not upon the ſame pretence of peace, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice moſt, if not all of the Ceremonies and Geſtures pertaining to the Maſs; granting him the liberty of a mentall abſtraction of them, from their Superſtitious and Idolatrous ones, I cannot yet underſtand; and what wonder is it, if there be of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions among you, when it is evident, that there are not a few of your Church, whoſe Ambition it ſeems to be, to run as nigh to the Romiſh Rights, as they may be ſuffered; not only in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doring, by bowing of the knee in the act of receiving of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; but in erecting the Communion Table in the form of an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar; and not only in bowing towards it, but being ready to kiſs the very ſteps that lead up to it. But if this were your mind, I can prove the contrary.</p>
            <p>But I know he will ſay, all this is nothing to our preſent caſe, for there are no ſuch errours or idolatrous Practices in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and therefore cannot be pleaded as a cauſe of our ſeparation.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, It is very difficult to know what the Church of <hi>England</hi> is; and how they ſhall we be able to underſtand what are the Truths or Errours ſhe maintaineth, or what are her Practices?</p>
            <p>If you ſhould take it to conſiſt of all the Chriſtians in <hi>England,</hi> whether Miniſters or People, ſo the Church of <hi>England</hi> would
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41103:35"/>Comprehend all Non-conformiſts Churches as well as others.</p>
            <p>If you take it for ſuch Chriſtians only who are of the Faith in Doctrinals with thoſe that hold with the 39. Articles; here the Non-conformiſts come in for a ſhare alſo, who are of your Faith therein: excepting thoſe which reſpect Diſcipline &amp; Ceremonies. But if you will take in, and own ſuch Chriſtians in <hi>England</hi> to be only of your Church, that agree with you in Ceremonies, and a certain form of Service and Diſcipline which Chriſt never Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and without which many of Chriſts Churches have and do ſubſiſt and flouriſh, to ſay no more, I wonder then, by what Goſpell Rule you preſume to conſtitute a Church only of ſuch, as excluſive of all others, however ſound in Faith and unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in life.</p>
            <p>Or ſhall we take your Church only to conſiſt of its officers; how ſhall we then Judge of your Faith, and Doctrinals? when ſo many of your Miniſters are ſo contrary one to another. Some are for the doctrine of Predeſtination, and others againſt it: ſome are for Juſtification by Imputed righteouſneſs, others not: ſome for a difference betwixt Grace and Morality, others oppoſe it: Some for the divine right of Epiſcopacy, others that the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate may appoint what form of government he pleaſes: in a word, ſome write or approve of ſuch a book, that others of you think (as I have heard) fit to be burnt. Which of theſe ſhall we underſtand to be your Church?</p>
            <p>If thoſe only, that meet by authority, in your Conſiſtory, to adviſe of what is fit for the reſt to believe and Practiſe; What then becomes of the Church, when that Conſiſtory is diſſolved and ſent home.</p>
            <p>But what if a Conſiſtory concludes of the 39. Articles, and the Preachers when all is done preach the quite contrary in ſeveral weighty points (As it is conceived many of yours do) and theſe are not only tollerated but encouraged by preferments, &amp; conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently owned by your ſelves? but you have a ſalve for all this, for you tell us, let ſome (and why not many or moſt?) preach Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines contrary thereto, yet your Church is very ſound in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſo long as the XXXIX. Articles remain to be her Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. But I wonder how theſe Articles may be called your
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41103:35"/>Doctrines, if but for fear, your Miniſters or People ſhall believe them, according to the true intent and meaning of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilers.</p>
            <p>But in the mean time, what a ſad Condition muſt the poor People be in, when ſuch corrupt Teachers ſhall be impoſed on them, if they are bound (for fear of Schiſme) to ſit under their corrupt Doctrines to the endangering of their Faith, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of their Salvation, yea though they be errours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine of your own Church.</p>
            <p>If you ſay, the people have liberty (in this caſe) of complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, but to what purpoſe? when ſuch errours are publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſt in Printed Books, and no courſe taken for the correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or ejecting of the Authors, which ſhall hold their places with encouragements?</p>
            <p>If you ſay they may then withdraw, and joyn with other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, provided they be of the ſame Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer then, what is become of your propoſitions, that er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors only tollerated, are no juſt ground for ſeparation?</p>
            <p>If you ſay, they may be juſt ground of ſeparation from a particular Congregation, but not from a National Church.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, but what if the whole National Church ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guilty of the ſame or like errours: what, is it a juſt ground Then to withdraw? if you ſay no, I demand for what reaſon? I can not think of any, except theſe two: that to ſeparate from a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, ſo we joyn with another of the ſame National Church, doth not run us upon the ſame danger, as if we ſeparated from the whole; for the latter leaves us deſtitute of all publick ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages to our ſelves, which the other doth not. Beſide, the publick honouring of God in his Worſhip, which is every Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Duty, would be neglected.</p>
            <p>My further reply is this, that if the honouring of God in publick, and my Souls ſafety, are the only reaſons that are to ſway in this matter, then in the pertaking with Churches, though Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, where both theſe may be obtained, the ſeparation will be lawful, and conſequently it will be lawful to ſeparate from a Church upon the only cauſe of its having corrupt Doctrines in it tollerated, though not impoſed. If you ſay there is a law of the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41103:36"/>Land that makes it unlawful to joyn with a Church ſeparate from the National:</p>
            <p>I anſwer, then the queſtion will be only this; whether the Law of a Land, or the ſecurity of my Faith (and conſequently my Salvation) ought more to be regarded? which I think is very eaſy to determine.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid, it is evident, that ſome ſort of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in a Church, though but tollerated, may be a juſt ground of withdrawing; though I do not charge the Church of <hi>England</hi> with any ſuch errors, nor had I ground, provided her Miniſters did honeſtly believe thoſe Articles that they have profeſſed to believe; which (as is conceived) ſeveral of them do not. So that what as to this point I have ſaid, is pleadable only by ſuch private Chriſtians whoſe lot it is to fall under the Teaching of ſuch Conformiſts, who are ſuch Non-conformiſts to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as that they dare deride ſome ſober Chriſtians under the notion of being acquainted with the Perſon of Chriſt, or that dare Teach there is no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Grace and Morality; or that there is no ſpecial Grace ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erted in the converſion of a ſinner, or that the Holy Ghoſt is of no further uſe in the Converſion of men, than as he firſt inſpired thoſe that delivered the Doctrine of Chriſtianity in Scriptures, and ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſuch to confirm the Truth of it with Miracles, ſo that men are left in the working out of their Salvation, to their Bibles and the uſe of their natural Faculties, excluſive of any other operation of the Spirit; either to their illumination or ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I ſay, if the People withdraw from ſuch Teachers or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, where ſuch Doctrines are owned, for ſecuring their Faith or Salvation, there ſo doing is juſtifiable; becauſe the law-of ſelf preſervation, is to be regarded before any poſitive law of viſible Church Union; and I hope there is no true Son of the Church, that hath any zeal for the purity of their Church Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, will be my adverſary herein: and thus much ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to be ſaid concerning your Doctrines, and of the lawfulneſs of ſeparating from ſome of the particular Congregations, in caſe the Teachers do groſſely pervert Some of the weighty Doctrines of your own Church.</p>
            <p>We ſhall in the next place conſider what you have here offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as to corrupt practices, which you ſay is no juſt ground (if
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41103:36"/>only tollerated, but not impoſed) of withdrawing, eſpecially if they be no worſe than are found in the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, firſt, if all the corrupt practices in your Church were only tollerated but not impoſed, you would have much more reaſon of your ſide againſt us, than you have, becauſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral things which you enjoyn to be practiſed, we in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences believe to be unlawful; and we cannot, muſt not, have Communion with you except we comply therein, ſo that ſhould it be yielded, that unimpoſed corruption in a Church, is no juſt ground of ſeparation, yet is it of no force againſt us, becauſe ſome of theſe we conceive to be corruptions, are impoſed.</p>
            <p>But to come cloſe to the caſe as it ſtands related to this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, ſuppoſe no impoſition of any of thoſe things that are in controverſie between us; which is the ſuppoſition in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: what will follow, but firſt that all the Miniſters of Chriſt in <hi>England,</hi> would be capable of places? for they are Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions that are the principal reaſons why they are kept out. Secondly, it would follow, that thoſe that are for the uſe of the Liturgy and Ceremonies, and a promiſcuous Communion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all that had but the name of Chriſtians, in the Sacraments, might therein act according as they ſaw fit, and as for other Miniſters they might freely exerciſe their Miniſtry without Liturgy or Ceremonies, and might exerciſe Diſcipline toward their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpective Members according to Chriſt's direction in the caſe.</p>
            <p>The queſtion now ariſing can be only this; whether it would be lawful for a Member of that Congregation where the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy and Ceremonies are in uſe, and Diſcipline neglected that conceived theſe things to be corruptions, to ſeparate and joyn with another; free from theſe conceived corruptions. I ſay he might firſt, becauſe were ther is no impoſition, ther can be no law of Superiors binding him to a Communion with ſuch a conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed corrupt Church: ſo that your great reaſon (ordinarily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in this caſe) would be of no force here. Secondly, becauſe that it is much ſafer for his ſoul to be joyned to a pure Church than a corrupt, and ſelf preſervation is founded on a law Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or to that of viſible Church-Union, to this or that particular Church. <hi>David</hi> might eat of the Shew-Bread to ſave his life,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:41103:37"/>which had not been lawful; if poſitive laws were not to give place to natural.</p>
            <p>Thus have I examined the third poſition, both generally, and as it particularly reſpecteth our preſent differences; and ſhewn both its unſoundneſs in the former, and impertinency as to the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; I have onely one word to ſay to the Reaſon given, upon which the ſuppoſed Truth thereof is founded, and ſo ſhall diſmiſſe it.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why he ſays that Errors in a Church, as to matter of Doctrine; and corruptions, as to matter of practice; if but ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered and not impoſed, is on juſt ground for ſeparation: becauſe theſe things are not ſins in us, ſo long as we do not joyn with the Church therein.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, if he mean that other mens Errors or Corruptions are not properly or formally mine by being in their Company, and joyned with them in things lawful, I grant it. But yet it follows not, that therefore I may joyn with them if I can other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways help it; a man may buy and ſell, and eat and drink with Fornicators, or other unclean and Debauched Creatures, if he cannot trade and get proviſion for his body but in their Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. But certainly, if a Trade might be as well managed with ſober men, and that Meat may be had in better Company, it would be ſinful then to Trade and Eat with ſuch; and why? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the law of ſelf preſervation warranteth me in the former, but not in the latter: I may not neglect the preſervation of my life by eating, nor geting a lively hood by trading, which is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily neceſſary to the preſervation of my life, &amp; preſent being, A meer occaſion of hardning others in ſin, or ſcandalizing weak Brethren; but when no ſuch neceſſity doth lye on me, then the preventing of a ſcandal, or giving occaſion to the hardning others in the their ſin, and the ſafety of my ſelf from their contagion, are reaſons of force to bind me from ſuch Societies.</p>
            <p>In like manner, if the Word of God could be no where heard, or Communion in Sacraments no where enjoyed, but only in ſuch Churches that were ſo corrupt as yours is conceived to be; it might be Lawfull, yea and a Duty to joyn with you, ſo far as poſſibly Chriſtians could without ſin. But if other Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es may be had, which are regular according to Gods law, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41103:37"/>irregular according to mans, then it is a Duty to withdraw, to prevent ſcandals, and hardning a Church in its Corruptions, together with the preſervation of themſelves from the danger of being infected with thoſe Corruption, which are reaſons of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nature, than that only one which you give; for though (as I ſaid,) by joying with ſuch, I make not their ſins formally mine, yet I ſin therein, upon other accounts now named which may juſtifie my withdrawing.</p>
            <p>I come now to his fourth which is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the enjoying of a more profitable Miniſtry, or living under a more pure Diſcipline in an other Church, is no juſt Cauſe of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the Communion of that whereof we are members. Becauſe we are not to commit the leaſt Crime, for the attaining of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt good in the World, now it is a Crime to for ſake Communion with a Church of which we are members, where we may continue without ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, Whatever may be thought of this poſition, I am perſwaded that the reaſon annext, is too weak to bear the weight of it: for the reaſon ſuppoſeth that which is not to be ſuppoſed: that is to ſay, that to withdraw from a Church, for the benefit of a more profitable Miniſtry, is a Crime. You call it a crime, becauſe you ſuppoſe it is a tranſgreſſion of the Law of viſible Communion, with ſome particular Church; but I ſay that the Laws of Viſible Communion, with this or that Particular Church are but poſitive, and therefore ſubordinate to laws more naturall and neceſſary, ſuch is that wherein we are commanded to take care of our ſouls and ſalvation. So that if Chriſtians do ſhift par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches for the obtaining of very apparent advantages to their Salvation, above what they could have had where they were, I ſee therein no crime at all committed, except ſuch an one wherewith the Phariſees charged our Saviour, as the Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sabbath, that he might heal the ſick. Certainly the cure and Salvation of ſick Souls, as of ſick Bodies, is of greater account with God than keeping to Pariſh Churches, or the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of a day.</p>
            <p>Sure I am, that very many Souls, that have for many years lain Blind and Dead in treſpaſſes, under their Pariſh Miniſters. (I ſpeak not partially as to thoſe only that are now in place, but
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41103:38"/>formerly when the Non-conformiſts held their places) but upon changing of their Miniſter, received their conviction, and reall Converſion, I dare ſay it would be a very hard Task to convince ſuch of the ſin of ſeparation in ſo doing.</p>
            <p>I have much wondered that men ſhould think it but reaſonable that every man ſhould be permitted to chuſe his own Phyſitian, and who will blame one that is ſickly if he (waveing the advice of his Neighbour, though a Phyſitian) ſhall apply himſelf to the moſt skillfull and ſucceſsfull that he can hear of for his health; &amp; yet that it ſhould be accounted ſo criminal to uſe the ſame care for a mans ſalvation. And what though the Phyſitian I ſpeak of, be not of the Colledg, nor can be ſuffered to be thereof. becauſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he will not ſwear to the truth of all the Aphoriſms of <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> or the truth of all and every part of the Colledges diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations: who think you, will ſtand upon ſuch a Nicety, if he yet believes him exceeding skillfull and ſucceſſefull in the cure of ſuch diſtempers under which he groaneth? and certainly when you have writ your ſelf a weary to prove the contrary, yet men herein will follow the Conduct of their Reaſon, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct of Self-Preſervation: which is not only ſeen verified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Non-conformiſts, but among your ſelves. What elſe is the reaſon, that ſome of your own Churches are thronged with auditors, when in others, the People ſit thinly ſcattered, like the gleanings ofter Harveſt? and I think it almoſt as eaſie to ſtop the Sun in its courſe, or the Sea in its flowing, as to prevent theſe concourſes of the People to ſuch Miniſters that are eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moſt able and ſucceſſefull. Thus much I have ſaid concerning the Reaſonableneſs of forſaking Communion with one Church, for the obtaining a more profitable miniſtry in another. The next thing to be examined is, that which you have ſaid concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the unlawfullneſs of for ſaking one Church, to enjoy a more pure Diſcipline in an other. To this I ſay it muſt be confeſſed, that a regular execution of Church Diſcipline, as it was ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt for great ends: So, when ſo executed it is found of very great uſe and benefit to the Church, for thereby is there a means provided to inform the ignorantly ſinning members, to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the Wilfull, to reclaim Apoſtates, to eſtabliſh and confirm the ſound, that their Souls may be ſaved in the day of the Lord
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:41103:38"/>Chriſt. And certainly, a neglect of this Diſcipline, muſt be a very dangerous conſequence to a Church, and to the Salvation of its members. And therefore if Chriſtians withdraw from ſuch a Church where this Diſcipline is next to wholly neglected, to joyn with another where it is exerciſed to the great advantage of its members; I ſee no ſin therein, as this author imagineth. For ſhall I ſay, the Law of Self-preſervation, is ſuperior to the Law of Viſible Union to a Particular Church, and therefore muſt firſtly be obeyed. May Parents Lawfully Change a School for their Children, where the Schollars by connivance, are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to Curſe and Swear, &amp;c. and yet are kept in the School, eſpecially if great Mens Children: perhaps ſome poor mans childe, for ſome one of theſe ſins, may now and then be caſt out but readmited upon very ſlender ſatisfaction. I ſay, may Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in this caſe, (tendering the Souls of their Children) remove them to another, and yet be blameleſs? I wonder then why it ſhould be ſo Criminal for a Chriſtian to remove from ſuch a Church, where ſuch ſins are in like manner tollerated; for the benefit of a better Diſciplined Church.</p>
            <p>True, if Learning was as neceſſary as Chriſtianity, and if no other School could be had; it were better their Children to be kept in ſuch a School, than to be ſuffered to run about the ſtreets to their more certain ruine. For the Rule of Practice to every Chriſtian in this caſe, is, of two evils to chooſe the leaſt: But as things ſtand with us in <hi>England,</hi> there are more pure Diſciplined Churches to be had, and therefore no Chriſtian can be thought to be in ſuch ſtraits. If ye ſay, theſe more pure Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciplined Churches are irregular, as not having the Eſtabliſhment of an humane Law: I anſwer, it is not neceſſary; For the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Churches, and their Eſtabliſhment; is founded on a Law of Chriſt, and not on Humane Laws. Chriſts Miniſters have a right to Preach the Goſpell, and Gather Churches, and Govern them by his Rules; without the leave of any Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates. The powers of the Earth may be Nurſing Fathers to the Church, but as ſuch, they neither give them their Being or Conſtitution. When Chriſt ſent the firſt Preachers of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, to Diſcipline Nations, and gather to him Churches, he did not direct them firſt to ask the Governours of thoſe Nations
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41103:39"/>leave ſo to do: for his own Commiſſion was warrant ſufficient without their Licence: but when God is pleaſed to ſtir up the hearts of Princes to give leave and encourage the work, it is a great Bleſſing; which Chriſts Miniſters are to pray for, and to be greatly thankfull when they have it.</p>
            <p>Yet again, I anſwer, that thoſe Churches are moſt Regular that are Taught and Governed with the greateſt conformity to the Rule of Chriſt, and if thoſe of the Non-conformiſts prove ſuch, I know not why any ſhould be blamed for joyning with them upon the account of their irregularity.</p>
            <p>Thus have I anſwered this Fourth poſition of yours, and have ſhewed how far an unprofitable Miniſtry and Corrupt Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline in your Church, gives ground of ſeparation from you.</p>
            <p>His Fifth and Laſt Propoſition.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>That though we have a juſt Cauſe to refuſe Communion with the Church whereof we are members, in ſome inſtances; yet we are not therefore to proceed to ſo total a ſeparation from it, as to Erect a New Church in Contra-diſtinction to it, or to joyn with thoſe that do.</hi> The Reaſon he gives is, <hi>becauſe we are bound to obey as far as we can, but at no hand to diſturb the Peace.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>To the Reaſon I Briefly anſwer, that theſe Miniſters and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple obey as far as they can, when they by obeying neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſin, or what they ſuſpect to be ſin, or when they neglect not ſome known duty; <hi>Daniel</hi> might not obey when he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid praying for ſome days to the true God: But for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt not to go on in their Miniſteriall work, and for the People not to enjoy all ordinances, is to neglect known duties, in ſome things only, and not in theſe they ſuſpect, and therefore ſuch a ſeparation is Lawfull, notwithſtanding his Reaſon, and now I anſwer to the Propoſition: I may very well doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this propoſition be univerſally true, when this very Author, himſelf grants it is not, <hi>For if a Church be ſo greatly and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Corrupt in Doctrine and Practice, as the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>ſo that the Salvation of thoſe that Communicate with her be indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger'd,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41103:39"/>it is then not only lawfull to ſeparate, but to Erect a new Church:</hi> this he confeſſeth in a very few lines following. Thus he hath provided wiſely good ſhelter for himſelf &amp; his, from the firſt charge of his propoſition with reſpect to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whileſt he hath left the poor Non-conformiſts to ſhift as they can with reſpect to their own Church; but by his leave I ſhall make bold with his own evaſion, for a covert to them alſo from this ſtorm, for what though the Corruptions and Doctrines and Practices be not ſo great and ſo generall in an other Church, as theirs in the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> yet if they be but ſo many, and ſo great as to endanger their Salvation, it is ſufficient to warrant ſuch a ſeparation.</p>
            <p>And now (if you will give me leave) I will tell you how theſe People concieve their Salvation is indangered, through your corruptions. If they ſhould not ſeparate as they do, I ſay then, Theſe outed Miniſters (do not wonder) if they conceive it is by reaſon of the corruptions, that many hundreds of them have been caſt out and ſilenced as much as in them lies: and why? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will not ſwear and forſwear, aſſent and conſent to all that they would have them, by reaſon whereof they are redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to theſe ſtraits, either to ſwear and do as you would have them, and that againſt their Conſciences: or elſe to wrap their Tallants (through ſlaviſh fear, like ſlothful Servants) in a Nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin; and forſake the work of the Miniſtry, which their Lord has intruſted them with: if they do the former, they like wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Hypocrites will go againſt their own Conſciences, and ſo will indanger their Salvation, or elſe like falſe and treacherous Stewards, muſt deſert their maſters work and ſo incurre the doom of ſuch Stewards; ſo that let them look on the right hand or on the left, they ſee nothing but damnation; what then is left for them to do but to go on in their work as now they do for their own ſafety, that is to Preach, Teach, Father and Rule his People, which you are pleaſed to call the erecting of new Churches, which (as I ſaid) is no more than to do the duty of Chriſts Miniſters, and therefore cannot juſtly be charged on them as their ſin. You call theſe erected Churches new, and what if they be new in reſpect to the time of their riſe, that is not their fault, but if you conſider them with reſpect to their
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41103:40"/>rule, either of their Worſhip or Government, ſo they may be more Antient than your own; for ſuch Societies of Chriſtians that meet with Chriſts Miniſters to worſhip God according to the way of the Goſpel Churches. without impoſed Forms of Prayer, or without the uſe of any ſuperſtitiouſly impoſed veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or when they meet, to Adminiſter Sacraments without any impertinent ſuperſtitious uſe of the ſign of the Croſſe, or to Eat the Supper in a Feaſtival poſture, as Chriſt and his Apoſtles did, or ſuch Churches that are governed by Chriſts Officers, (and ſuch Presbyters unqueſtionably are) not by lay Chancellors, unheard of in the firſt Churches, where nothing is impoſed on the Members, but what Chriſt by command hath made neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and nothing cenſured as ſcandalous and threatned with Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communion, but that that is an evident tranſgreſſors of Gods laws, as Drunkenneſs, Whoredome, Swearing are in a manner conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at, or if at any time cenſured in ſome poor People, the cenſure is upon very ſlight grounds taken off, upon a very ſlight and formal Repentance, or the payment of a few groats. But where the tranſgreſſion of a Ceremonious law, or a Tradition of the Elders, is dealt with as a ſin unpardonable, fines, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſilencing, baniſhments, Excommunications are puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments all thought little enough for ſo great a ſcandal. Let now any man well conſider both theſe ſorts of Churches, both as to their way of Worſhip, Adminiſtration of Sacraments, or way of Government, and then tell me whether of them are more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the Antient Apoſtolical pattern, and ſo which of them deſerve the name of old, and which of new Churches. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, peradventure you will ſay, that we have broke the Unity of the National Church, which we ought to have preſerved.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, we have but broke it by accident, and you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive but by accident, for no man can be ſaid to ſin, or to be a Peace-breaker when he is but doing his duty; and I conceive it hath been proved that we do no more: <hi>Elijah</hi> was charged with being the troubler of Iſrael, and the Apoſtles with turning the world upſide down, and yet they were faultleſs. But you ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41103:40"/>are breakers of it <hi>per ſo,</hi> for do but you impoſe no more up-us than Chriſt our Lord hath done, either by Himſelf or his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as neceſſary conditions of Communion, and be but you willing to receive theſe as Miniſters and Members which Chriſt receives and owns, and I dare ſay we ſhall ſoon enjoy a bleſſed Peace, and that upon Righteous Foundations which Chriſt would certainly bleſs and cauſe to laſt; but if you will drive us to ſuch ſtraits as that either we muſt wound our Conſciences by a ſinful compliance with you, at leaſt, with ſuch a compliance that we ſuſpect ſinful, or elſe live in the neglect of our known duties and without the enjoyment of ſome Ordinances. I beſeech you blame us not for what we do, for you your ſelves have made it neceſſary: this I think is a ſufficient anſwer to your fifth and laſt propoſition, which being all you have ſaid that directly concerns us, I ſhall take the boldneſs to conclude with your own words, <q>I am verily perſwaded that I have ſaid nothing in this my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, but what is very agreeable to Scripture and reaſon, and the ſence of the beſt and Antienteſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> Apoſtolical Chriſtians and Churches.</q>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
